<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">Live Orthodoxy</title>
<generator uri="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.liveorthodoxy.com" />
<updated>2016-11-29T11:29:27-06:00</updated>
<id>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/</id>
<author>
  <name>Thom Crowe</name>
  <uri>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/</uri>
  <email>thom@thomcrowe.com</email>
</author>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Giving Thanks]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/giving-thanks/" />
  <id>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/giving-thanks</id>
  <updated>2016-11-24 05:34:25 -0600T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2016-11-24T00:00:00-06:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Thom Crowe</name>
    <uri>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com</uri>
    <email>thom@thomcrowe.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;We Orthodox are a thankful bunch; we give thanks to God when we wake in the morning and before we go to sleep, during our hours of prayer and during the Divine Liturgy. Our whole lives are a time for us to offer thanks to God.  That doesn’t negate the fact that I love Thanksgiving, the day that we as a nation take some time to pause and reflect on the many blessings we each have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year has been a big year for us in our house and I’d like to take a few moments to share my gratitude. In February, our sweet little Elise was born, a healthy beautiful baby girl. For the past nine months, we have been blessed to watch her grow, learn and develop her personality each and every day. I’ve watched her laugh, crawl, talk, stand, wave, point and learn to make everyone around her laugh. She’s the single most precious thing in our lives, and I can’t begin to offer any thanks to God that would be worthy of the most incredible blessing I have in my life. I get to share this experience with my best friend, my beloved companion, my partner in crime, my wife. We wouldn’t have her if it weren’t for her birth mother and father, to whom we are also grateful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the grace of God, I was ordained to the holy diaconate. I am thankful every week when I stand in front and kiss of the altar and when Father George places the body of Christ in my hand. It is a great responsibility, and I thank God that I can serve our parish and the Holy Church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am blessed to have a loving and supportive family, on my side and Christine’s. Our friends and church family add to our lives and help us as we help Ellie grow up to be the amazing girl I know she will be.  They are so much more than I deserve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know we offer thanks every day, but today, I’m taking the time to share my thanks for everything God gives me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Everlasting King, Thy will for our salvation is full of power. Thy right arm controls the whole course of human life. We give Thee thanks for all Thy mercies, seen and unseen. For eternal life, for the heavenly Joys of the Kingdom which is to be. Grant mercy to us who sing Thy praise, both now and in the time to come. Glory to Thee, O God, from age to age.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/giving-thanks/&quot;&gt;Giving Thanks&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Thom Crowe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com&quot;&gt;Live Orthodoxy&lt;/a&gt; on November 24, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Forget Being Politically Correct]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/forget-being-politically-correct/" />
  <id>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/forget-being-politically-correct</id>
  <updated>2015-11-02 08:34:25 -0600T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2016-11-22T00:00:00-06:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Thom Crowe</name>
    <uri>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com</uri>
    <email>thom@thomcrowe.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;I wish I could claim originality in my inspiration for this, but I can’t. An author and blogger I follow &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.ancientfaith.com/nearlyorthodox/&quot;&gt;Angela Doll Carlson&lt;/a&gt; shared a thought on a Facebook group we’re both a part of that caused me to pause and think - &lt;em&gt;“Stop talking about whether or not something is politically correct. Ask instead whether if is kind. Let’s aim for kindness.”&lt;/em&gt; For some reason, this struck me - if we could just focus on showing kindness, how much better would things be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;love-is-kind&quot;&gt;Love is Kind&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re all familiar with what Christ taught in Matthew 22:36-40:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“You shall love the Lord your God with all your heart and with all your soul and with all your mind. This is the great and first commandment. And a second is like it: You shall love your neighbor as yourself. On these two commandments depend all the Law and the Prophets.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is love? Among other things, it is kind, as St. Paul tells us in 1 Corinthians 13. It’s something we as Christians are called to, kindness. Political correctness, in theory, centers around the idea that all people deserve respect and honor. We don’t use terms to describe people that they consider offensive, we don’t marginalize or demean someone based on their ethnicity, gender, age, intelligence, disability or other traits. And yet I count the number of times I’ve heard statements like, “I know this isn’t politically correct, but…” from Christians and non-Christians alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Angela’s post left me thinking about kindness in our everyday lives. Is it kind to discriminate, make sexist or sexual comments, to demean another person, to use terms that would offend someone? No, it most certainly isn’t. If it isn’t kind, then it isn’t love. If it isn’t love we are showing others, our neighbors, then it’s probably a safe bet to assume we are not living up to the call of Christ, we are not being strong ambassadors of Christ. I’m sure there are exceptions, but as a good rule of thumb, they go hand-in-hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s sad that in today’s society, I see so many people espousing hateful rhetoric, racism, sexism, and childish name-calling - Christians and non-Christians alike. There is no regard for political correctness, much less kindness. As a matter of fact, the word “political” is so divisive and polarizing. This election has, in my opinion, brought out the worst in people, on both sides of the aisle, and our society has taken a step back, or perhaps opened a door that had been shut for awhile. People say hateful things; others return in kind (I have had to repent for my words over the last few months). I found encouragement in reading the words of the Elder Thaddeus who taught:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It is not good when we return the love of those who love us, yet hate those who hate us. We are not on the right path if we do this. We are the sons of light and love, the sons of God, his children. As such we must have His qualities and His attributes of love, peace, and kindness towards all.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, we as Christians are called to a higher standard, to be more than that which is around us and now is a great time to work together to forget political correctness and focus on what we as Christians are called to do, and that’s to show love as Christ commanded. We can be a light in the world because, as St. John of Kronstadt tells us, &lt;em&gt;”Evil and faults are corrected by good, by love, kindness, meekness, humility, and patience.”&lt;/em&gt; St. Paul lays out what love is very clearly for us:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Love is patient and kind; love does not envy or boast; it is not arrogant or rude. It does not insist on its way; it is not irritable or resentful; it does not rejoice at wrongdoing but rejoices with the truth. Love bears all things, believes all things, hopes all things, endures all things.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;May we all look to all of our neighbors and find kindness in our hearts, offering prayers for those we agree with and those we don’t and answering the call Christ has set before us, to walk in love.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/forget-being-politically-correct/&quot;&gt;Forget Being Politically Correct&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Thom Crowe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com&quot;&gt;Live Orthodoxy&lt;/a&gt; on November 22, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sharing the Faith]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/sharing-the-faith/" />
  <id>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/sharing-the-faith</id>
  <updated>2015-11-01 08:34:25 -0600T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2016-10-16T00:00:00-05:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Thom Crowe</name>
    <uri>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com</uri>
    <email>thom@thomcrowe.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;I like to consider myself an amateur Orthodox apologist focusing on modern religious movements - amateur being the operative word in that sentence. When I’m traveling and I see the Jehovah’s Witnesses in a busy thoroughfare or in an airport, I always stop to pick up their newest Watchtower literature which I give a cursory read on the plane. While in Seattle a few weeks ago, I drove by the Mormon Temple and saw a group of missionaries in their perfectly pressed white shirts and ties and their Elder name badges. This got me to thinking about how we about something I don’t usually - at what we can learn from these groups and how they try to reach people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;knock-knock&quot;&gt;Knock knock&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I realized that both the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints and Jehovah’s Witnesses have a special passion for outreach and missionary work. This &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; seem obvious since they come to my house a few times a year and leave literature, but I had been so focused on where they were off on doctrinal issues, that I didn’t see an area where we as Orthodox Christians are missing the mark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mormon and Jehovah’s Witness members all commit to missionary work. It looks different for both groups: young Mormon men and women receive training before devoting themselves to missionary work - young men go for two years, young women for one year. They are assigned to a certain geographical area and given a partner to work with and make themselves busy going door-to-door sharing their faith. Jehovah’s Witnesses volunteer to go out in groups from their local Kingdom Halls (what they call their parishes). Some go out with friends, some with their whole family, children included. Even Prince was known to go knocking on doors in his home town of Minneapolis. What is most troubling to me, is the effectiveness these groups see from these efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;and-what-do-i-do&quot;&gt;And what do I do?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While thinking on the level of commitment they give to sharing their faith, I was troubled my own personal lack of missionary mindedness for outreach and spreading the Gospel. I’m not advocating that we as Orthodox Christians need to develop hard and fast rules for going door to door throughout the world knocking and going through a rigid training program or using books with appendixes that we can flip to and give a textbook answer for any question that could come up. That’s not what Orthodoxy is about and that’s not how historical Christianity has gone about witnessing the Gospel of Christ, but I do think we need to look at the great commission we have from Christ to,”…..” and find how to live that call.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When is the last time you invited a friend to Church? How about a friend who isn’t religious? It’s easy for me to talk to my Evangelical friends about Holy Orthodoxy and share the fullness of the faith, but I’m not usually the best about sharing as deeply with the unchurched, the agnostics or the atheists I know. Part of this is from my background as an Evangelical where, at least in my Church, we militantly talked about Christ’s sacrifice and how our decisions here on earth affect the afterlife, without carrying the grace needed to have those conversations. That’s at least part of the reason so many people are turned off from Christianity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-whats-the-answer&quot;&gt;So what’s the answer?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, I don’t have a quick and easy answer, but I have some ideas we could use as a starting place for a bigger dialogue together. I know there are wonderful members of the faithful who are reaching out and would be far more suited to lead this discussion and I hope to find some who would be willing to teach the rest of us. We also have a wonderful missionary effort through groups like IOCC and men and women who give up everything and move their families to work throughout the world sharing the Gospel. But what about those of us here at home - what can we do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;invite-friends-to-church&quot;&gt;Invite friends to Church&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This seems simple enough. I try to bring many of my friends to our parish. I find services like the Pashca Rush and Liturgy, the blessing of the waters at Ephipany, feasts that don’t fall on Sundays, Vespers and Lityas to be nice intros to Orthodoxy. It’s great to bring friends, but it’s also important to prep them for their first visit.  An Orthodox service can be overwhelming, many people aren’t use to the sights, sounds and smells of Orthodoxy so a little additional time spent explaining these things is helpful. Point out examples in the Scriptures of how we worship (singing of the Psalms in Collasians 3:16 and  Ephesians 5:18-20, incense is used in Heaven throughout the book of Isiah, Daniel and Revelation, the Apostles prayed “the prayers” in Acts 10:2-3, the Early Church used a liturgical calendar as we see in Acts 20:6 and 1 Corinthians 16:8).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;pray&quot;&gt;Pray&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Christians, we are called to “pray without ceasing,” and we try to do this as we pray for friends and family, follow our daily prayer rule, remember the Jesus Prayer all throughout the day, but there are times where we can easily pray with our friends. When we are eating out at a restaurant, ask if your friends will pray with you. I have yet to have anyone object to praying for a food blessing with me. In our house, we pray before each and every meal so this isn’t unnatural for us, as it won’t be for most of you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;visit-food-and-ethnic-festivals&quot;&gt;Visit Food and Ethnic Festivals&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have two festivals here in Tulsa, Greek Fest at Holy Trinity and Hafli at my parish, St. Antony. I &lt;strong&gt;love&lt;/strong&gt; bringing friends to the festivals. It’s a fun, non-threatening way to introduce people to Holy Orthodoxy and you’re helping to support a parish since these are usually fundraisers. Check the schedule and see if there are tours that you and your friends can go one because there is always something that we can learn as well. Our priest does amazing tours and I always walk away with something new.  If there aren’t tours, or a tour time doesn’t work for you, ask if a deacon, subdeacon, reader or someone else at the parish can lead a tour or get a blessing from your priest to do a tour for your friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an aside, our temples are powerful witnesses to Christianity and Orthodoxy. I had been reading about Orthodoxy while at college. When home for Christmas break, I visited St. George Houston and met now Khouria Gigi Shadid. My friends and I were supposed to meet with the priest but there was a miscommunication on what time we were coming, so we were blessed with a tour for Khouria Gigi. She explained the layout of the parish, the icons, the altar and how these come to life and engage Christians during worship. When I left, I told my friends I was home. I came back to college, met my now spiritual Father and told him I wanted to join the Church. These can be powerful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;offer-to-host-an-event-or-talk&quot;&gt;Offer to Host an Event or Talk&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this doesn’t work, talk to your priest and see about doing a community event. When our bishop came to visit a few years ago, His Grace Bishop +BASIL did an enlightening talk on the Theotokos that was great for the Orthodox and non-Orthodox alike. After the movie &lt;strong&gt;American Sniper&lt;/strong&gt; came out, it inspired our priest to do an amazing talk about the movie and how it applies to our spiritual life. Father George, who is a combat vet from Vietnam, talked about his experience and the work of spiritual warfare, pulling things from the movie that most of us never would have caught. We had a few talks because the community was so interested in the presentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;share-something-from-ancient-faith-radio&quot;&gt;Share something from Ancient Faith Radio&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here in America we are blessed to have Ancient Faith Radio. They have podcasts on almost any topic you could imagine. You can send a friend a link or download a podcast and put it on a thumb drive. Their blogs are great too. I would love it if friends would read books, but that’s a commitment and if they aren’t yet interested in Orthodoxy, that can be tough. AFR has great blogs that you can share that can be read in 5 or 10 minutes, something most people are willing to commit if you offer it to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;be-the-light&quot;&gt;Be the Light&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We as Orthodox have a great opportunity to be the light of Christ, to show His love in our daily lives. We do this by not engaging in gossip or hateful conversations, helping those around us, praying for and with those in need, practicing Christian hospitality and countless other ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we all try some of these, I think we could easily bring Orthodoxy to more people, sharing the faith in a practical and real way. We don’t need to engage in arguments or debates, Bible thump or anything like this. St. Paul calls us ambassadors of Christ, and this is what we are called to be, meaning we are to act as Christ, preaching and living the Gospel in love.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/sharing-the-faith/&quot;&gt;Sharing the Faith&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Thom Crowe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com&quot;&gt;Live Orthodoxy&lt;/a&gt; on October 16, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to Parenthood]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/welcome-to-parenthood/" />
  <id>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/welcome-to-parenthood</id>
  <updated>2016-03-26 23:34:25 -0500T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2016-03-27T00:00:00-05:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Thom Crowe</name>
    <uri>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com</uri>
    <email>thom@thomcrowe.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve been jotting down notes periodically about our new life with Ellie and am now starting to take those random notes and write about our experience. Here’s the first one I’m ready to share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-6&quot;&gt;Day 6&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Elise awoke, at 1:00 am this morning, the third time already tonight since I laid down at 11:00, I got up and went through our usual routine. She’s only been home for 4 days, but we’ve begun developing a new normal together. I’m new to parenting and I’ve already learned it’s trial by far because newborns aren’t the most patient creatures on the planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I picked up our precious baby to check and change her diaper. After that, I stared into her little eyes, darting around trying to take in everything around her before becoming fixed on my face. I smiled and kissed her. Her precious little mouth pursed and she stuck her tongue out a few times. She was telling me she was hungry the only way she knew how. So we walked to the kitchen and I made her a bottle. We came to the couch and sat down together, letting my wife sleep so she hopefully felt better the next morning. I turned on my phone and we listened to some chanting of the Psalms as she ate. Once done, I burped her and walked her back to her bassinet. We had been sleeping in our living room to get our two dogs use to the idea of this new furless puppy that they didn’t understand. Christine thought of placing her bassinet in front of our icon wall so Christ along with the Theotokos and the angels and saints could watch over her as she slept. As I looked at her there so peacefully asleep, it hit me, I had been praying &lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt; Elise, but hadn’t prayed &lt;em&gt;with&lt;/em&gt; Elise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew it was late, we were well past the setting of the sun, but I grabbed our prayerbook and, holding her in one arm and swaying, Elise and I prayed Vespers together. Sure she slept and made tiny human sleep noises in my ear, but I held her close and prayed out loud. I love Vespers, it’s a service that really resonates with me everytime, most likely because of my deep interest in the creation story. I can read the first three chapters of Genesis 1,000 times and still feel like there’s more that I’m not getting it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was our routine for a few nights, but the prayerbook became cumbersome and difficult to navigate while holding a baby. That’s when I switched the &lt;a href=&quot;http://orthodox.seasidehosting.st/current_service&quot;&gt;Dynamic Horologion&lt;/a&gt; on my phone. It’s a perfect way to pray with a baby. I can easily hold it in one hand and, now that I wear her in her &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.boba.com/&quot;&gt;Boba wrap&lt;/a&gt;, I can use my other hand to caress her back. Plus, it has the current service available and all of the variable changes for the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know she’s not old enough to understand what’s going on around her yet, but I can’t help but to feel that hearing the words of the prayers and the Psalms at a young age is just planting another seed we’ll continue to nurture over her lifetime, doing what we can to guide her in Orthodoxy towards Christ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;O God, our heavenly Father, who loves mankind and are a most merciful and compassionate God, have mercy upon Your handmaiden Elise for whom I humbly pray to You to care for and protect. O God, be her guide and guardian in all her endeavors, lead her in the path of Your truth, and draw her nearer to You, so that she may lead a godly and righteous life in Your love as she does Your will in all things. Give her Your grace, and mercy so that she may be patient, hard working, tireless, devout and charitable. Defend her against the assaults of the enemy, and grant her wisdom and strength to resist all temptation and corruption, and direct her in the way of Salvation, through the goodness of Your Son, our Savior Jesus Christ, and the prayers of His Holy Mother and the blessed saints. Amen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/welcome-to-parenthood/&quot;&gt;Welcome to Parenthood&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Thom Crowe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com&quot;&gt;Live Orthodoxy&lt;/a&gt; on March 27, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Living Liturgical Tradition]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/a-living-liturgical-tradition/" />
  <id>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/a-living-liturgical-tradition</id>
  <published>2016-02-09T17:58:02-06:00</published>
  <updated>2016-02-09T17:58:02-06:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Thom Crowe</name>
    <uri>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com</uri>
    <email>thom@thomcrowe.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;I feel like I should get this out of the way before we get started here: I love the liturgy. I really do. I’ve been a part of a liturgical tradition for 15 years now, nearly half of my life and I honestly can’t imagine not participating liturgically in my worship of God. With that out of the way, you’ve been warned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went to a crowning service last weekend for a couple of kids who joined the Orthodox Church a few weeks ago. For the non-Orthodox here, an Orthodox wedding is like something you’ve most likely never seen. The most striking difference for most first timers is that we don’t do vows. I’ll probably delve into the reasons and rationale behind that later, but I’m trying to stay focused. Instead, we have a betrothal, crowning (with literal crowns), a procession called the Dance of Isiah and drinking from a common cup. It’s really a pretty awe-inspiring service. I studied it in my grad work and then was asked to help put together an explanation for my godson and his wife when they got married and the more I learned, the more I loved the service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back on topic, I was serving at a crowning service last weekend.  The couple had been married outside of the Orthodox Church before they joined and this was a service in which the pr&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;St. Paul tells us in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Ephesians+5%3A20-34&amp;amp;version=ESV&quot;&gt;the wedding epistle&lt;/a&gt; that this is a &lt;em&gt;profound mystery&lt;/em&gt;, the term we Orthodox use for Sacraments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What struck me so much during the wedding, despite all of the Orthodox weddings I’ve attended, is what I &lt;em&gt;didn’t&lt;/em&gt; remember, or, better stated, what didn’t jump out at me. This wasn’t a new experience for me. I gain a new perspective or new insight into what marriage means and what marriage is. As a side note and a personal soap box here, this is part of the reason I try to attend all weddings at our parish (baptisms, chrismations and funerals as well) - these are family events and we, as Christians, especially of the same parish, are a family, we are brothers and sisters in Christ and these events should be shared and celebrated  with one another, with those of us from the parish praying for the couple, the baby, the initiate or the reposed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the beauty of the liturgical life. When I attend a wedding, I hear the priest pray over the couple and confer God’s blessing on them. The Epistle from the service reminds us that marriage is selfless. By attending weddings at our parish, the beauty of my marriage is continually reinforced as is my role as a husband. As I’m joining the Church in praying for this new couple, I am also praying for myself, my wife and our union.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is true in all of the services and mysteries of the Church. When I attend a baptism or chrismation, I relive my baptism, my chrismation. The same is true for the Epiphany/Theophany service - with the prayers of the blessing of the waters and the rememberance of Christ’s baptism, my own baptism is brought to mind. This isn’t by accident. When we relive the events in the life of Christ, of the Virigin Mary, of the Saints and of the Church, these events are reminders of salvific experiences in our lives. At the Nativity of Christ, we are reminded that we are partakers of the divine nature because of Christ’s humanity; at Transfiguration, we are called to be Transfigured; at the Feast of the Elevation of the Cross, we are reminded that we too died with Christ in the waters of baptism that we may be raised with him; at the Annunciation, we are reminded of the call to choose Christ we answered; at Pentecost, we are reminded of the outpouring of the Holy Spirit on us at our Chrismation; at each and every Eucharistic service, we are reminded of the Eucharist we took when we became members of the Church. Not only are these things from the past that we remember or meditate on, they are recreative events that we participate in anew each and every time if only we are receptive.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/a-living-liturgical-tradition/&quot;&gt;A Living Liturgical Tradition&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Thom Crowe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com&quot;&gt;Live Orthodoxy&lt;/a&gt; on February 09, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[This I Believe - Creeds in Chrisitianity]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/this-i-believe/" />
  <id>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/this-i-believe</id>
  <updated>2016-01-02 02:04:25 -0600T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2016-01-02T00:00:00-06:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Thom Crowe</name>
    <uri>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com</uri>
    <email>thom@thomcrowe.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TL:DR- Doctrine matters. It’s not possible to truly be one with diverse teachings. This is why we have creeds - to preserve the faith delivered once and for all - the faith handed to the Apostles by Christ and preserved unconquered by the Holy Spirit’s operation in the Church.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;but-who-do-you-say-that-i-am---mark-829&quot;&gt;“But who do you say that I am?” - Mark 8:29&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Jesus asked this question to the Apostle Peter nearly 2,000 years ago, he asked a question that would need to be answered by each and every person who would come in contact with the Gospel. As Christianity spread, and the number of those who professed a faith in Christ grew, the number of interpretations of that question also grew, some times to the detriment of believers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-a-creed&quot;&gt;What is a Creed?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creed comes from the Latin word &lt;em&gt;credo&lt;/em&gt; meaning “to believe.”  I know for many Protestants, the term Creed is far too restrictive and formal, so they’ve developed their own statements of belief or confession of faith; despite what it may be called, it is ultimately a Creed.  For the Orthodox Church, no Creed is more widely expressed than the Nicene Creed (sometimes called the Nicene-Constantinople Creed).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creeds are not unique to Christianity; Judaism professes the &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shema Yisrael&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;“Hear O Israel, the Lord is our God, the Lord is One”&lt;/em&gt; Deuteronomy 6:4) and Islam professes their creed, the shahada which says, &lt;em&gt;“There is no god but God; Muhammad is the messenger of God.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;creeds-in-the-new-testament&quot;&gt;Creeds in the New Testament&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the early Church, there were simple creeds that addressed the problems that faced the various Churches. A great example is what is referred to as the &lt;em&gt;Pre-Pauline Creed&lt;/em&gt; of 1 Corinthians 15:3-7 which says,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For I delivered to you as of first importance what I also received: that Christ died for our sins in accordance with the Scriptures, &lt;strong&gt;that he was buried, that he was raised on the third day in accordance with the Scriptures,and that he appeared to Cephas, then to the twelve. Then he appeared to more than five hundred brothers at one time, most of whom are still alive, though some have fallen asleep. Then he appeared to James, then to all the apostles.&lt;/strong&gt; (English Standard Version).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s called the Pre-Pauline Creed because it is a creed that Paul is obviously quoting, which existed before he was converted as we see from his statement, “which I also received” in verse 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;St. Paul again quotes part of an early creed when he writes to St. Timothy 3:16, &lt;em&gt;”We confess, is the mystery of godliness: He was manifested in the flesh, vindicated by the Spirit, seen by angels, proclaimed among the nations, believed on in the world, taken up in glory.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these are a continual development of the Church answering Christ’s question, “Who do you say that I am?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-creed-of-the-early-church&quot;&gt;The Creed of the Early Church&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as the different New Testament communities developed creeds to ensure safe guards around correct teaching, the Early Church had issues that arose and they too needed to define doctrine.  The most well known Creed in Christendom is the Nicene Creed.  In the fourth century, a doctrine was spreading that denied Christ’s divine nature called Arianism. This doctrine threatened the sound Christian doctrine and our understanding of who Christ is.  The leaders of the Church came together in the city of Nicea and all 318 successors to the Apostles unanimously agreed on a formula to articulate the person of Christ.  This formula became the Nicene Creed.  The faithful members of the Church affirm this belief regularly to safe guard against false teaching.  The beauty of the Creed is best explained by the late Yale professor, Dr. Jaroslav Pelikan who said, &lt;em&gt;”The singing of the creed is a very important and cherished way of indicating a universality of the faith across not only space but time — to know that in the Philippines this morning, this was the creed that was recited and to know that the Emperor Justinian in the sixth century and my late father and grandfather all affirmed this, all of us together.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-does-it-matter&quot;&gt;Why does it matter?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s this idea of unity between several strains of Christianity that exists outside of doctrine. It seems to me that there’s laissez-faire attitude towards doctrine and belief, that an understanding of the nature of God, man, salvation, etc is of less importance than a semblance of unity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, I’ve heard several Christians say they are Christians because of a unique experience or a feeling they get. I’m not going to say that there’s no place for personal feelings or experience within Christianity, but instead that it isn’t all we need.  Those of other faiths heavily draw on the emotions and personal experiences.  Take for examples the Latter-Day Saint (Mormon) missionaries. When they begin visiting with non-LDS about the LDS Church, they cite from their Doctrine &amp;amp; Covenants (one of their books of scripture along with the Bible, Book of Mormon and Articles of Faith) and claim Christ said &lt;em&gt;”But, behold, I say unto you, that you must study it out in your mind; then you must ask me if it be right, and if it is right &lt;strong&gt;I will cause that your bosom shall burn within you; therefore, you shall feel that it is right&lt;/strong&gt;.”&lt;/em&gt; (D&amp;amp;C 9:8)  When talking to someone who joins the LDS church, they will confirm the burning in the bosom as their proof of faith. When faith and truth are based primarily on experience, how does one question the validity of something like this? People join the LDS church despite the fact that they teach things outside of the Nicene Creed and historical Christian teachings, like God was once a man who was elevated to God. When no emphasis exists on truth and correct doctrine, doors like this are left wide open.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If people are taught to base their religious belief solely on emotional responses, how can they be  &lt;em&gt;”prepared to make a defense to anyone who asks you for a reason for the hope”&lt;/em&gt; found in the Gospel (1 Peter 3:15)?  The Apostles never appeared to anyone and discussed how they were made to feel by an encounter, but instead they boldly and firmly proclaimed the teachings of Jesus Christ and the revelations of the Prophets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even in the New Testament there were those who changed the teachings delivered by the Apostles and, as St. Paul taught, &lt;em&gt;”a little leaven leavens the whole loaf”&lt;/em&gt; (Galatians 5:9). The Epistles of St. John were written in large part to encourage the faithful to remain steadfast in right doctrine and not to follow false teachers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why the New Testament warns us to, &lt;em&gt;”watch out for those who cause divisions and create obstacles contrary to the doctrine that you have been taught,”&lt;/em&gt; and not to &lt;em&gt;”be led away by diverse and strange teachings”&lt;/em&gt; (Romans 16:17; Hebrews 13:9). Instead, we are encouraged to &lt;em&gt;”keep a close watch on yourself and on the teaching. Persist in this, for by so doing you will save both yourself and your hearers”&lt;/em&gt; 1 Timothy 4:16.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The successors to the Apostles took the teachings and traditions handed to them and passed them to their successors and preserved them. That’s the goal of a creed - to give the faithful within the community a set of boundaries of safe doctrine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;after-all-christ-called-us-all-to-be-one-right&quot;&gt;After all, Christ called us all to be one, right?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, it’s not possible to truly be one with diverse teachings.  &lt;em&gt;”For the time is coming when people will not endure sound teaching, but having itching ears they will accumulate for themselves teachers to suit their own passions, and will turn away from listening to the truth and wander off into myths”&lt;/em&gt; (2 Timothy 4:3-4). The creeds give us formulas of doctrine that explain what we believe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like what the &lt;em&gt;Orthodoxy &amp;amp; Heterodoxy&lt;/em&gt; blog has to say on the matter, &lt;em&gt;”Theology is not just life and death, but _eternal&lt;/em&gt; life and death. We have to get it right not just so we can belong to the right churchy club, but so we can grab hold of sanity in an insane world, so we can seek out the profound while surrounded by triviality, so we can pursue beauty in the midst of ugliness…Doctrine includes not just dogma, but every teaching and true tradition pertaining to union with the Holy Trinity—worship, asceticism, hierarchy, canonical tradition, and so forth. Doctrine is what we are taught and what we teach.”_  If we are not committed to getting that right, what are we committed to?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why we have creeds - to preserve the faith delivered once and for all - the faith handed to the Apostles by Christ and preserved unconquered by the Holy Spirit’s operation in the Church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-nicene-creed&quot;&gt;The Nicene Creed&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I believe in one God, the Father Almighty, Maker of heaven and earth, and of all things visible and invisible; And in one Lord, Jesus Christ, the Son of God, the Only-begotten, Begotten of the Father before all ages, Light of Light, True God of True God, Begotten, not made, of one essence with the Father, by Whom all things were made: Who for us men and for our salvation came down from heaven, and was incarnate of the Holy Spirit and the Virgin Mary, and was made man; And was crucified also for us under Pontius Pilate, and suffered and was buried;	And the third day He rose again, according to the Scriptures;	And ascended into heaven, and sitteth at the right hand of the Father; And He shall come again with glory to judge the living and the dead, Whose kingdom shall have no end. And I believe in the Holy Spirit, the Lord, and Giver of Life, Who proceedeth from the Father, Who with the Father and the Son together is worshipped and glorified, Who spoke by the Prophets; And I believe in One, Holy, Catholic and Apostolic Church. I acknowledge one Baptism for the remission of sins. I look for the Resurrection of the dead, And the Life of the age to come. Amen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/this-i-believe/&quot;&gt;This I Believe - Creeds in Chrisitianity&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Thom Crowe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com&quot;&gt;Live Orthodoxy&lt;/a&gt; on January 02, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[“Mary Did You Know?“]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/mary-did-you-know/" />
  <id>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/mary-did-you-know</id>
  <updated>2015-12-16 02:04:25 -0600T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2015-12-16T00:00:00-06:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Thom Crowe</name>
    <uri>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com</uri>
    <email>thom@thomcrowe.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;h2 id=&quot;its-just-a-christmas-song&quot;&gt;It’s Just a Christmas Song&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve had a few conversations with people this year about the song &lt;em&gt;”Mary Did You Know?”&lt;/em&gt;  and it’s been interesting to hear how others feel about the song.  I’ve never really been a fan, namely because of how overly sentimental it feels to me, but this year I gave some thought to the meaning behind the song.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-whats-wrong-with-it&quot;&gt;So What’s Wrong With It?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, I’m not going to throw everything out and say that some how Mary knew each and every thing that would happen throughout Christ’s life. When songwriter Mark Lowry asks if Mary knew &lt;em&gt;”that your Baby Boy would one day walk on water?”&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;“that your Baby Boy will give sight to a blind man?”&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;”that your Baby Boy will calm the storm with His hand?”&lt;/em&gt;, that’s valid theological speculation. We don’t really know if Mary knew those things. She could have been prophetic and foresaw some of those miracles that Christ would perform or maybe not, we’ll never know. But we do know that Mary had knowledge of the great power that Christ possessed as witnessed in the Gospel story of the wedding feast at Cana. When they ran out of wine for the feast, it was Mary who went to Christ to turn the water into wine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those questions aside, I do take issue with some of the other questions that songwriter Mark Lowry asks. Questions like, &lt;em&gt;“did you know that your Baby Boy would save our sons and daughters?”&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;“did you know that your Baby Boy has walked where angels trod? When you kiss your little Baby you kissed the face of God?”&lt;/em&gt; These questions are outside the bound of theological speculation and land straight into a bad understanding of who Mary is and her relationship to God and her son.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s just look at what the Archangel Gabriel told her whom he called full of Grace and pronounced the Lord was with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Do not be afraid, Mary, for you have found favor with God. And behold, you will conceive in your womb and bear a son, and you shall call his name Jesus. He will be great and will be called the Son of the Most High. And the Lord God will give to him the throne of his father David, and he will reign over the house of Jacob forever, and of his kingdom there will be no end.” Luke 1:30-33.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gabriel made it pretty clear who Jesus was to anyone knowledgable of the Scriptures. Since Mary was a faithful Israelite who had been taught the writings of the prophets, Mary knew what the angel meant. And these weren’t things she forgot. The nativity story in Luke tells us that &lt;em&gt;“Mary treasured up all these things, pondering them in her heart”&lt;/em&gt; Luke 2:19. At Christ’s birth and as He grew, she knew He was God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-do-i-care&quot;&gt;Why do I care?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mary is a saint I hold near and dear to my heart. As a young Evangelical, I dismissed the Mother of God and outright attacked her. To me, she was just another woman, nothing special, just an instrument of God. He could have chosen anyone. That’s not the whole story. Mary is a normal person, just like you and me, but she’s also so much more. She’s is extraordinary; despite the fact God &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; have chosen anyone, He didn’t - He chose Mary. She devoted herself fully to God, remained faithful to Him and gave her only son up to be crucified before her very eyes. As an aside here, I’ll make note that Mary was more faithful than 10 of the disiciples who had fled in fear from the crucifixion. She was the first Christian as she literally accepted Christ into her body. She was faithful when all hope seemed lost. She serves as an example of what faith in Christ should look like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we teach about Mary is also direct reflection of what we teach about Christ. When we call Mary the &lt;em&gt;Theotokos&lt;/em&gt; (God-bearer or Mother of God), we are calling her that because Christ is both fully God and fully man. She gave birth to God through the Incarnation. We call Mary the second Eve because, just as Eve chose to sin and thus ushered death into the world, Mary said yes at the Annunciation and brought forth life into the world. We call Mary &lt;em&gt;“more spacious than the Heavens”&lt;/em&gt; because she contained the God who all of creation could not contain within her womb. Just as she did during her life, everything about Mary continues to point to Christ, to call us to her Son.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we diminish Mary, who she is or her knowledge of what she agreed to, we begin to diminish who Christ is. Without a doubt, Mary knew she kissed the face of God, she knew who Christ was and what His birth meant, both for her and for all of humanity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that, I join the angel and St. Elizabeth in singing,  “Hail Mary, full of grace, the Lord is with you. Blessed are you among women and blessed is the fruit of your womb.”&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/mary-did-you-know/&quot;&gt;“Mary Did You Know?“&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Thom Crowe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com&quot;&gt;Live Orthodoxy&lt;/a&gt; on December 16, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Most Wonderful Time of the Year]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/the-most-wonderful-time-of-the-year/" />
  <id>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/the-most-wonderful-time-of-the-year</id>
  <updated>2015-26-24T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2015-11-26T00:00:00-06:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Thom Crowe</name>
    <uri>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com</uri>
    <email>thom@thomcrowe.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Christmas is an exciting time and it is so easy to lose focus on why we’re celebrating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things are changing, the hot days of summer are gone and people have started pulling out the sweaters and coats, more so this year than most thanks to the polar vortex that brought some lovely snow to us here in Tulsa this weekend. This weather was perfectly timed with the start of the Fast of the Nativity to get me to thinking about Christmastime and how we as Orthodox Christians engage during this time year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growing up, Christmas was my favorite time of the year. The holiday was a really BIG event in our evangelical/charismatic church. We would do a candle light service every year where we would sing hymns. This felt Christmassy to me. Then when I was in high school, I attended a candle light mass at a Catholic church with a friend and that was pretty cool too. The churches were all decorated with greenery, big nativity scenes and we had the carols. I associated all ofthese things and songs with Christmas. When I became Orthodox, I really missed the way I had celebrated Christmas growing up a lot of that and really thought out how to reconcile that celebration with my new-found Orthodox celebration.Thirteen Christmases later, I have a few thoughts on this for others who have joined the Church or are looking into it. While this was originally meant to be a single blog post, like so many other times in my life, I found myself adding more and more and more, so this week I’m going to focus on Advent and Christmas music with more to come next week.this will be continued into next week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;advent--the-nativity-fast&quot;&gt;Advent – the Nativity Fast&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our fast in the East begins on November 15th. I personally need the fast to help me stay focused on exactly what we are preparing to celebrate. The world around us is in a frenzied state of hyped up consumerism and unchecked revelry. Even many Christians in the West forget the purpose of the season leading up to Christmas. As everyone else is spinning out of control, the fast reminds us that we need to slow down and focus on Christ. The Incarnation, God becoming man, is an universe-altering event, that we need to really stop and reflect upon. As Orthodox Christians, we fast to bring us closer to God, not because we have to,for show or to create unfair hardship. Saint Cosmas of Aitolia instructs, “Fast according to your ability, pray according to your ability, give alms according to your ability.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-better-time-than-nativity&quot;&gt;What better time than Nativity?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important part of any fast is participation in the liturgical life of the Church. We have rich hymnography and services throughout Advent. To keep everything in focus, the church gives us hymn lyrics like this: “Make ready, O Bethlehem: let the manger be prepared, let the cave show it’s welcome. The truth has come, the shadow has passed away; born of a Virgin, God has appeared to men, formed as we are and making god-like the garment He has put on. Therefore Adam is renewed with Eve, and they call out: ‘Thy good pleasure has appeared on earth to save our kind.’” It is during this time that we remember Israel awaiting the arrival of the Christ child that we know is coming in a few weeks, so that when we arrive at the great Feast, we can sing as St. Symeon the God-receiver, “Lord, now you are letting your servant depart in peace, according to your word; for my eyes have seen your salvation that you have prepared in the presence of all peoples, a light for revelation to the Gentiles, and for glory to your people Israel.” Why does this matter? St. Maximos the Greek (4th century, not to be confused with St. Maximos the Confessor) wrote, “Unless the Lord comes to us, we are completely helpless.” Without the Incarnation, without the birth of Christ, we would not have the door to salvation that has been opened to us through His glorious Resurrection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;christmas-music&quot;&gt;Christmas Music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love Christmas music. I really do. Like, really really love Christmas music. It was always something that was a big deal to listen to in my home growing up and the songs were always a part of church life as well, one of the few vestiges of a liturgical life left in the religious tradition in which I grew up. Over the years, I’ve listened to Western Christmas hymns and studied them to ensure what I was hearing and singing was aligned with Orthodoxy. For the most part, I was really glad to learn that they were. I’m not talking the Jingle Bells or Rudolph or Christmas Shoes songs, I’m talking the O Come, O Come Emmanuel, Angels We Have Heard on High,  God Rest Ye Merry Gentlemen songs. These are amazing. O Come, O Come Emmanuel recalls the need Israel had for a savior, the need all of humanity had for Christ. O Come All Ye Faithful calls the faithful to celebrate the birth of Christ together. Away in a Manager recalls Christ’s birth (though I’d like the cave to be mentioned somewhere in there). The Little Drummer Boy gives us images of finding the Christ child in the manager. We Three Kings recalls the journey of the Magi, Kings from the East, coming to worship the Heavenly King humbled as a young babe. Others like The First Noel, Good King Wenceslas, I Saw Three Ships, Joy to the World, and O Little Town of Bethlehem are great songs to listen to and sing during the Nativity Fast as they continue to point us to Christ and the real reason for the season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others I learned to be leary of. It Came Upon a Midnight Clear was written by a Unitarian with the intent of removing the Incarnational reality from Christ’s birth and Christmas. Unitarians are quick to point out that “the Christ-child is never mentioned” because it is “ethical song, extolling the worth and splendor of peace among men.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That being said, it’s so important to incorporate the beauty of the Orthodox hymnography into Christmas celebrations. I’d venture to say, it’s not possible for one to keep Christ in Christmas more than the Orthodox Church has. If you want to hear some good Orthodox Christmas music, check out the CD Make Ready, O Bethlehem by Anaphora. I can’t really let you hear it here, so I’ll just share some of the beautiful poetry in our Christmas tradition:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Christ is born! Glorify Him!
Christ descends from the heavens, welcome Him!
Christ is now on earth, O be jubilant!
Sing to the Lord, the whole earth,
And sing praises to Him with joy, O ye people,
For He has been exalted!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What shall we present unto Thee, O Christ,
For Thy coming to earth for us men?
Each of Thy creatures brings Thee a thank-offering:
The angels — singing; the heavens — a star;
The Wise Men — treasures; the shepherds devotion;
The earth — a cave; the desert — a manger;
But we offer Thee the Virgin-Mother. O Eternal God, have mercy upon us.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today doth Bethlehem receive Him
Who sitteth with the Father for ever”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I behold a strange but very glorious mystery:
Heaven — the cave;
The throne of the Cherubim — the Virgin.
The manger — the receptacle in which Christ our God,
Whom nothing can contain, is lying*&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thy Nativity, O Christ our God,
Has illumined the world like the Light of Wisdom&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;… They who worshipped the stars were through a star,
Taught to worship Thee, the Sun of Righteousness,
And to know Thee, the Day-Spring from on high&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/the-most-wonderful-time-of-the-year/&quot;&gt;The Most Wonderful Time of the Year&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Thom Crowe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com&quot;&gt;Live Orthodoxy&lt;/a&gt; on November 26, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Keeping Christ in Christmas]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/keeping-christ-in-christmas/" />
  <id>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/keeping-christ-in-christmas</id>
  <updated>2015-11-17 02:04:25 -0600T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2015-11-17T00:00:00-06:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Thom Crowe</name>
    <uri>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com</uri>
    <email>thom@thomcrowe.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;h2 id=&quot;a-few-thoughts-on-the-international-refugee-crisis&quot;&gt;A Few Thoughts on the International Refugee Crisis&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s that time a year that Christmas trees and decorations adorn shop windows, Christmas songs are playing, and people everywhere are beginning the hustle and bustle of preparing for the holiday season. At the same time, I see signs around that say &lt;strong&gt;“Keep Christ in Christmas.”&lt;/strong&gt; While I don’t disagree with this sentiment I find these words to be especially hollow this year and feel a little like Charlie Brown (see the header image?).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watching the news, I saw a list of states that have all made an effort to ban refugees from the Middle East. And you know what caught my eye about many of these states? They are the ones that have elected officials who identify themselves as Christians. For those of you who don’t know, I’m in Tulsa, Oklahoma, the buckle of the Bible belt. Our governor professes to be a Christian as do a majority of voters in our state, yet we are trying to refuse refugees fleeing from a land torn by violence at the hands of terrorists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the angels greeted the shepherds in the fields, they proclaimed a message that Christians sing every Christmas, &lt;em&gt;“Glory to God in the highest, and on earth peace, good will toward men.”&lt;/em&gt; Are we living that good will in our lives, especially offering good will to some of the most vulnerable people, when we are turning a blind eye to our brothers and sisters in their suffering and time of need?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lest we forget, Christ our Lord was a refugee. The Apostle and Evangelist Matthew tells us that after Christ was born, his mother and Joseph had to flee from Israel and make a new home in a strange land because the tyrant Herod was slaughtering innocents throughout Israel. Even after they were told they could return to Israel, they weren’t able to go home but instead made a new home in Nazareth (Matthew 2:13-23). As Christians, we are known by our love for one another and closing ourselves off from those in need is not a sign of love (John 13:35).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of these refugees are fleeing from Syria right now and several of those are our brothers and sisters in Christ. Syria was a cradle of Christian civilization in the Early Church. St. Paul had his conversion on the road to Damascus, which is in present day Syria. Christians were first called Christians in Antioch which sits on the boarder with Syria and is where St. Paul and St. Barnabas began their missionary journey. Christians in Maaloula still speak Aramaic, the language of Christ. Believers have lived in this region since the time of Christ. As I read about the sister diocese to my diocese in Bosra-Hauran in Syria, my heart breaks. The Christian population has been decimated in Syria from those fleeing the violence, abductions and enslavement of Christians at the hands of terrorist groups from within their own country. We are talking up to 2 million Christians who are suffering right now. Those are just the Christians, not counting the others caught in the middle of this conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we remember what happened last week, the violent attacks by a terrorist groups in Paris, it seems our media has overlooked the violence in Beirut. I’d encourage everyone to read &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/elio.nicolas1/posts/1115113775167118?fref=nf&amp;amp;pnref=story&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; for some insight into those events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reaction we’re seeing within our own country and I’m reading from Christians is not one in keeping with the teachings of Christ. Let’s remember what Christ told the righteous in Matthew  35:40:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For I was hungry and you gave me food, I was thirsty and you gave me drink, I was a stranger and you welcomed me, I was naked and you clothed me, I was sick and you visited me, I was in prison and you came to me.’ Then the righteous will answer him, saying, ‘Lord, when did we see you hungry and feed you, or thirsty and give you drink? And when did we see you a stranger and welcome you, or naked and clothe you? And when did we see you sick or in prison and visit you?’ And the King will answer them, ‘Truly, I say to you, as you did it to one of the least of these my brothers, you did it to me.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of watching the news and reading articles about what companies aren’t saying, &lt;em&gt;“Merry Christmas,”&lt;/em&gt; or building a defense against the &lt;em&gt;“War on Christmas”&lt;/em&gt; let us watch our hearts and look at how we’re treating others who are in need, our brothers and sisters who are enduring through something so unimaginably horrific.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us also remember the words that grace the Statue of Liberty: &lt;em&gt;“give me your tired, your poor, your huddled masses yearning to be free.”&lt;/em&gt; These are the people we are saying aren’t welcome here. If we are going to turn our heads and ignore the huddled masses yearning for freedom, we might as well take down Lady Liberty since she holds her lamp as a beacon. Taking Christianity out of the discussion, serving as a refuge is a part of our country, the reason for the founders of our country to come to our shores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we all make our preparations for Christmas, filling out cards, buying gifts, visiting friends and families, let us not forget what the Lord has called us to do. Let us not close our borders to those in need. Let us be vigilant and watchful for the will of the Lord so that when Christ returns, he will find us ready, like the wise virgins with their oil and the doors to the feast will not be closed to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to leave off with this beautiful prayer that I will be adding to my prayer rule during this Advent/Nativity season:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Lord Jesus Christ, our God, You said to Your disciples, “Peace I leave with you; my peace I give to you; not as the world gives do I give to you.”  We come before You in humility and ask that Your peace which surpasses all understanding will descend upon all people around the world, especially those currently in conflict and at war. Increase understanding and forgiveness between nations.  Awaken the longing for a peaceful life in all those who are filled with hatred for their neighbor.  Extinguish every dispute and banish all temptations to disagreement. Grant wisdom to civil authorities.  Free those held captive, protect those in danger, and comfort those who are suffering and displaced.  Implant in all of us reverence for You, and confirm us in love for one another.  Make us worthy to celebrate the feast of Your holy nativity and to join with the angels in chanting: “Glory to God in the highest, and on earth peace, goodwill towards men.” For You are the King of Peace and the Savior of our souls and to You we give glory together with Your eternal Father and Your most-holy, gracious and life-giving Spirit, now and ever and forever. Amen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/keeping-christ-in-christmas/&quot;&gt;Keeping Christ in Christmas&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Thom Crowe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com&quot;&gt;Live Orthodoxy&lt;/a&gt; on November 17, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[12 Things I Love About Orthodoxy]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/12-things-i-love-about-orthodoxy/" />
  <id>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/12-things-i-love-about-orthodoxy</id>
  <published>2015-06-19T07:58:29-05:00</published>
  <updated>2015-06-19T07:58:29-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Thom Crowe</name>
    <uri>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com</uri>
    <email>thom@thomcrowe.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;h2 id=&quot;full-disclosure&quot;&gt;Full Disclosure&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;)I’ve wanted to write a listicle about the Orthodox Church, my home within Christianity, for quite some time. But, as often happens, I got distracted and never finished it, until today. So what changed? I saw an &lt;a href=&quot;http://benirwin.me/2015/01/22/11-things-about-the-episcopal-church/&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; shared by my friend &lt;a href=&quot;http://audreyeclectic.blogspot.com/&quot;&gt;Heather&lt;/a&gt; about the 11 things someone loves about the Episcopal Church. It inspired me to write this, not as a rebuttal or anything like that, but to share some of what in Orthodoxy keeps me connected to Christ, to the Church and to my brothers and sisters in Christ. That being said, thank you Ben and Heather for the inspiration and I hope I can do justice to the beauty of Orthodoxy._&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-journey-to-orthodoxy&quot;&gt;My Journey to Orthodoxy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I joined the Orthodox Church almost 14 years ago after feeling lost within the Charismatic/Evangelical world. I was attending Oral Roberts University and had way too many questions to know where to even start. I had begun studying some Church History and was at a point where I was torn between Catholicism and Anglicanism, not feeling terribly comfortable with either option and my roommate was considering Messianic Judaism. The two of us were longing for something we couldn’t find and got to a point where we got a $1 loaf of french bread and bottle of grape juice to have communion in our room because we didn’t really know where we belonged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then one night, I was in someone’s dorm and saw a copy of &lt;a href=&quot;http://books.google.com/books/about/Eastern_Orthodox_Christianity.html?id=2B8lAQAAIAAJ&quot;&gt;Eastern Orthodox Christianity: A Western Perspective&lt;/a&gt; on his table. While I don’t recommend the book, it was enough to get me asking what Orthodox was. I did some research online, ordered a ton of books, and got everything I could from the library. The more I read, the more I felt at peace about things I’d been questioning. I prayerfully read, started attending &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stanontytulsa.com&quot;&gt;my parish&lt;/a&gt; here in town and was chrismated into the Church and I’ve never looked back. Here’s why:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;i-dont-have-to-figure-it-all-out&quot;&gt;1. I don’t have to figure it all out.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Sunday mornings, when Fr. George begins to preach his homily, I listen and take what he teaches as spiritual food and edification. I do the same thing no matter which parish I visit because priests are connected to the Apostolic Tradition. They don’t spend time trying to think up new doctrine or theological opinions, because they participate in the continuation of the preaching and teaching (the kyrgma) of the Apostles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past 2,000 years, there have been countless heresy that have popped up around the world and tried to make in roads into the Church. Those heresies haven’t disappeared, but keep reemerging from various groups and some of them sound appealing. Without keeping constant vigil, it’s easy for one to begin to lean on one’s understanding or get carried off on a tangent that pulls away from the faith once delivered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve heard so many of my friends talk about how they didn’t agree with this pastor or that speaker and I remember the days in college when guest speakers would come and I became so skeptical that I was always waiting for an ax to drop. Some people I’ve talked to have said that’s just the way it is and sometimes their pastor or a speaker says great things and sometimes it’s “Biblically unsound.” Christ warned about false teachers, St. Paul warns against teachers who talk about things contrary to what has been taught and speculating in 1 Timothy, St. John warns about false teachers…the list could go on and on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within Orthodoxy, the Church has guarded the Truth and stands as the &lt;em&gt;”pillar and buttress of the truth”&lt;/em&gt; (1 Timothy 3:15). The Church has held councils as the Apostles did in Acts 15 and was led by the guidance and protection of the Holy Spirit as Christ had promised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;orthodoxy--orthopraxis-go-hand-in-hand&quot;&gt;2. Orthodoxy &amp;amp; Orthopraxis go hand in hand.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Orthodoxy has maintained, over the centuries, that it is the responsibility of the Church to preserve doctrine. Our very name is rooted in that tradition - &lt;em&gt;ortho&lt;/em&gt; meaning right or correct and &lt;em&gt;doxa&lt;/em&gt; meaning belief. &lt;strong&gt;Most&lt;/strong&gt; Christian traditions and sects have a concept of Christian belief, but what is missing is the idea of Christian Practice, or that there is even a concept of right practice. In Orthodoxy, the two are inseparable, but throughout much of the West this is a foreign idea. There is no hesitation or question of understanding when someone says that he or she is an Observant Jew, but there exists very little concept of an Observant Christian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our faith is put into practice in our doctrine and in our lives. The two are not mutually exclusive but built upon one another. As St. James tells us, we are “justified by works and not by faith alone” because “faith by itself, if it does not have works, is dead” (2:24; 17).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what does that look like? Within the Church, we &lt;em&gt;“stand firm and hold to the traditions&lt;/em&gt;” that were delivered by the Apostles, &lt;em&gt;”either by spoken word or by our letter”&lt;/em&gt; (2 Thessalonians 2:15). We are baptized for the remission of sins, receive the gift of the Holy Spirit, when we gather on the Lord’s Day, we participate in the Eucharist, we recieve the gift of confession, we celebrate together, we fast together, we mourn together…we work as one body of Christ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our every day lives, we are called to holiness, which we often miss. My praxis is challenged when I stand before the icon of Christ and confess our sins to Him in the presence of my priest and spiritual father who councils me and confirms God’s forgiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;we-worship-with-our-whole-being&quot;&gt;3. We worship with our whole being.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Orthodox worship engages all of the senses, taking worship out of a theoretical place, and grounding it here, in something tangible. We cross ourselves, offer metenias, prostrate, process - all forms of worship involving movement, engaging our bodies. As we look around, we are surrounded by the icons of Christ and His saints, we hear the chanting and the bells, we smell the incense, we taste the fountain of immortality in the Eucharist - our whole person is engaged in worship, as it should be because, after all, when God created us He said, “It is good.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our senses being engaged in worship speaks to our view of humankind - we are not evil. Our bodies are not evil. We weren’t created to die, the separation of body and soul is a consequence of the fall, not part of God’s design. Our free will separates us, but it was Christ’s incarnation, a good and loving Christ who put on humanity, that redeemed the material world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;orthodoxy-is-connected&quot;&gt;4. Orthodoxy is connected.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I go to an Orthodox Church, I know what to expect. Every Orthodox Church, throughout the entire world will be participating in the same liturgy I am. I am part of something much larger, part of communities of people I’ve never met with languages and cultural customs I know nothing about. A few years ago, I visited a Serbian parish that was near my parents. I &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; have done my research, but I didn’t and when I got there the entire liturgy was in Serbian. Despite the fact that I obviously don’t understand more than a couple of Serbian words, I was actively involed in the liturgy. I knew what the priest was saying, I knew what the chanters were chanting and I was able to participate in this glorious service, commune and fellowship with my brothers and sisters in Christ after service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the connection is deeper - as I look at the icons on the walls, I am connected with those saints. I am praying the same prayers they prayed, I am singing the same hymns they sang, I am receiving the same Eucharist they received. We are connected as the Church militant in a very real way to the Church invisible because,  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.esvbible.org/Hebrews+12/&quot;&gt;“we are surrounded by so great a cloud of witnesses” (Hebrews 12:1)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;we-dont-begin-or-end-liturgy-we-merely-join-in&quot;&gt;5. We don’t begin or end liturgy, we merely join in.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bible shows us insights into Heaven. In Isaiah, Daniel and St. John’s Apocolypse we see liturgical clothing, prayers and responses, censors and incense, lamps and lamp stands, candles, etc. There is an eternal liturgy taking place before the throne of God with angels and saints crying out to God. When we go to church, our services don’t begin and end, but we join into the prayers of the saints. We can again boldly confess that &lt;em&gt;“we are surrounded by so great a cloud of witnesses”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently we celebrated the Feast of All Saints. During Vespers we read, &lt;em&gt;“As is meet let us acclaim with sacred songs and laudations the divine assembly of the Apostles, Martyrs, and godly-minded priests, and the women most chaste, who throughout the whole world have contested in unshaken faith. For, though they were of earth, they were all united together with the Bodiless of Heaven’s heights, and by their august passion they received most blessed dispassion through Christ God’s grace. And now like steadfast stars that shine upon us, they intercede * with great boldness for our souls.”&lt;/em&gt; It is a beautiful feast that reminds us that the Church militant is not removed from the Church invisible, we share the same Great High Priest in Christ Jesus, the same joy in the hope of the resurrection, and the same prayers for the world and all of humanity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;orthodoxy-embraces-mystery&quot;&gt;6. Orthodoxy embraces Mystery.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an Orthodox Christian, I don’t have to try to explain everything. I know that God is bigger than I am and that my ways truly are not His ways. I know that at some point this saying has become a cliche in the West and, as my friend Jeff Huston pointed out, if you would have asked either of us in our pre-Orthodox days if we believed that, we would have said yes without question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we’re Orthodox, it means something…more. In Orthodoxy, we don’t spend our time reading and studying, trying to find a dogmatic reason for things. We don’t have to explain everything, but leave it to mystery. Take the Eucharist for example. We don’t have a doctrine of Transubstantiation or try to explain how the bread and wine are the body and blood of Christ; we know this to be true and it happens by some Divine Mystery.  As a matter of fact, what are called Sacraments in the West are called Mysteries in the East!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was working on my graduate studies, we spent a great deal of time reading about the unknowability of God. There’s an apophatic approach to describing God. Any terms or attributes that we can ascribe to God are limited and fall short, so we describe what God isn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;corporate-and-individual-worship-is-a-part-of-the-christian-life&quot;&gt;7. Corporate and individual worship is a part of the Christian life.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve heard so many people place emphasis on worship and devotion to God being an individual act and, to a degree, I can get on board. I pray to God, I read the Scriptures and writings of the Church Fathers, and try to sit in the stillness seeking God as all Orthodox Christians are called to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we go to church, all of our Orthodox Churches are all laid out the same - we walk into the narthex, enter into the nave and face the altar. The nave is like a ship carrying us all on the journey of life and faith towards Heaven. We participate in the Liturgy together, which, as its very name implies is the work of the people. We are saved both individually and as a community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;confession-is-freeing&quot;&gt;8. Confession is freeing.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a spiritual father, not just a priest, but someone who knows me inside and out, all of my deepest darkest secrets who helps me navigate through the Christian life. After I’ve prayerfully prepared for Confession, I go to our parish and stand with my priest before the icon of Christ at the front of our parish. As I confess, I make my confession to Christ and sometimes I’m granted the freeing tears of repentance. Once I’ve finished, Fr. George confirms Christ’s forgiveness and the remission of sins. But that’s not all, he counsels me with spiritual wisdom that helps me grow in Christ. The Church, through confession, helps us to rise up and become who we are supposed to be in Christ. We are conformed to the image and likeness of Christ. After I confess, I feel free. The sins that I’ve committed, both out in the open and those that I think have been done in secret, once confessed, lose their hold on me. I no longer feel the weight of guilt, but instead know that I can be more than who I am.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only is it freeing, it is Biblical. One of Christ’s final things Christ bestowed to His Disciples was the authority to forgive sins in Heaven and on earth. We believe the Bible to be inspired and have faith in the work of Christ. That authority to confirm the remission of sins is a great gift that far too many people have thrown aside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-liturgical-calendar-is-a-calendar-for-our-lives&quot;&gt;9. The liturgical calendar is a calendar for our lives.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I always loved Christmas - the decorations, the Christmas music we sang in Church, the reading of the Nativity story. Now I love the rest of the events in Christ’s life, along with the events of the Early Church as well lives of the Theotokos and saints and major events in the life of the Church throughout history. The Israelites remembered important days in which God intervened and helped them as Feast Days, days Christ and the Apostles kept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We celebrated Pascha (Easter) a few months ago, and every day we were reminded that we are in the Paschal season. During the Paschal Season, I find myself singing the Paschal troparion - &lt;em&gt;Christ is risen from the dead, trampling down death by death, and upon those in the tombs bestowing life!&lt;/em&gt; - and the Paschal antiphons, I greet other members of the Church by saying &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Christ is Risen”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, and look forward to seeing the Paschal candle every week at Church. After 40 days, we celebrated the Ascension, followed by Pentecost in another 10 days. August 6th is Transfiguration, the Church New Year is September 1st, the Nativity of the Theotokos follows on September 8th, then the Feast of the Elevation of the Cross on September 14th…you get the idea. Plus we celebrate our family members’ (and friends’) patron saint days (or, as we call them, name days). Our year revolves around the Church year. We fast, feast and celebrate together. We have customs and traditions in our parish and at our home. It brings our life in Christ and the life of the Church into our every day in a whole new, yet ancient, way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-church-conforms-us-we-dont-conform-it&quot;&gt;10. The Church conforms us, we don’t conform it.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the Civil Rights march in Selma, Archbishop Iakavos marched and stood next to Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. The Civil Rights movement didn’t alter the Church or change the Church, but the Civil Rights movement was rooted in the unchanging truths evident within the Orthodox Church. Orthodoxy doesn’t change every few decades depending on how society changes, but remains a true and steady witness to Christ throughout history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are called to holiness and the standard or measure of holiness is not something that is subjective or something that changes day to day. As things change or public opinion falters, the Church doesn’t change. Instead, we are called to change, as it should be. There is an idea today that we hold God to humanly standards and conform Him to our own image or ideals - instead we are still in a world in which we are ever changed and molded into God’s image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-liturgy-becomes-a-part-of-you&quot;&gt;11. The liturgy becomes a part of you.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never would have believed it at the time, but looking back, I can see that the churches I grew up in had their own liturgy. You go to church, there was upbeat fun music, it would slow down, the pastor would preach for 40 minutes, the lights would go down and slow music would start playing. It happened every week. While at ORU, I learned that there were formulas for this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within Orthodoxy, the liturgy we use is tried and true - most Sundays we pray the Liturgy of St. John Chrysostom, a liturgy that has been used by the Church since the 4th century!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liturgy guides us, it serves as a beacon in a storm-tossed world  that ensures we are oriented in the right direction and keeps our focus aimed for the Kingdom of God, not just some far off place, but helps us find the Kingdom that is within us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-church-knows-what-we-need-when-we-dont&quot;&gt;12. The Church knows what we need when we don’t.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week, a good friend of mine, our parish chanter, fell in asleep in the Lord. It was fairly sudden and caught me by surprise. While he was in the hospital, on life support, and I went to Vespers for All Saints. The readings were so aptly timed - (Isaiah 43:9-14, Wisdom of Solomon 3:1-9 &amp;amp; Wisdom of Solomon 5:15-6:3). It was comforting to hear the encouragement about the saints. After that, I went with my priest when he prayed the prayers for the departing of the soul from the body. It was emotional and I was lost. I didn’t know what to think, much less what to pray. He fell asleep later that evening. Then when I was at home, I was able to turn to the prayers of the Church which gave me comfort. Then, the following morning, we held a prayer service (Trisagian) for him. The Church was there to give us what we needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same is true of things like fasting. A mother gives her child the medicine he or she needs. I think we can all remember a time from childhood when we were sick and our mom gave us something that didn’t taste very good, but, in the end, it made us better.  The same is true for the Church. When I started in a prescribed fast, it was odd. At first, it was a challenge to overcome, I guess you could say I gamified fasting - if I do this, this, and this I win fasting. Then it was something I didn’t do for a long time or I would look for loopholes around fasting. But, when I started fasting, as tough as it was, it began to make sense. I had to put in the effort that the Church prescribed before I could understand the richness that is set there for usx by Christ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same is true of so many aspects of our lives - our services, our readings, our icons, confession, fasting, the lives of the saints - I could go on and on. The Church, as the body of Christ, is the great hospital for us on earth and is here to take care of us, even if we don’t know what we need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know some of these things may not sound earth shattering, but believe me they are. Something is different within Orthodoxy, it’s healing, it helps us to become whole, it continues the work of Christ in restoring humanity through the guidance and power of the Holy Spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/12-things-i-love-about-orthodoxy/&quot;&gt;12 Things I Love About Orthodoxy&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Thom Crowe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com&quot;&gt;Live Orthodoxy&lt;/a&gt; on June 19, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[12 Things I Love About Orthodoxy]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/12-things-i-love-about-orthodoxy/" />
  <id>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/12-things-i-love-about-orthodoxy</id>
  <published>2015-06-19T07:58:29-05:00</published>
  <updated>2015-06-19T07:58:29-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Thom Crowe</name>
    <uri>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com</uri>
    <email>thom@thomcrowe.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;h2 id=&quot;full-disclosure&quot;&gt;Full Disclosure&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I’ve wanted to write a listicle about the Orthodox Church, my home within Christianity, for quite some time. But, as often happens, I got distracted and never finished it, until today. So what changed? I saw an &lt;a href=&quot;http://benirwin.me/2015/01/22/11-things-about-the-episcopal-church/&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; shared by my friend &lt;a href=&quot;http://audreyeclectic.blogspot.com/&quot;&gt;Heather&lt;/a&gt; about the 11 things someone loves about the Episcopal Church. It inspired me to write this, not as a rebuttal or anything like that, but to share some of what in Orthodoxy keeps me connected to Christ, to the Church and to my brothers and sisters in Christ. That being said, thank you Ben and Heather for the inspiration and I hope I can do justice to the beauty of Orthodoxy.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-journey-to-orthodoxy&quot;&gt;My Journey to Orthodoxy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I joined the Orthodox Church almost 14 years ago after feeling lost within the Charismatic/Evangelical world. I was attending Oral Roberts University and had way too many questions to know where to even start. I had begun studying some Church History and was at a point where I was torn between Catholicism and Anglicanism, not feeling terribly comfortable with either option and my roommate was considering Messianic Judaism. The two of us were longing for something we couldn’t find and got to a point where we got a $1 loaf of french bread and bottle of grape juice to have communion in our room because we didn’t really know where we belonged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then one night, I was in someone’s dorm and saw a copy of &lt;a href=&quot;http://books.google.com/books/about/Eastern_Orthodox_Christianity.html?id=2B8lAQAAIAAJ&quot;&gt;Eastern Orthodox Christianity: A Western Perspective&lt;/a&gt; on his table. While I don’t recommend the book, it was enough to get me asking what Orthodox was. I did some research online, ordered a ton of books, and got everything I could from the library. The more I read, the more I felt at peace about things I’d been questioning. I prayerfully read, started attending &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stanontytulsa.com&quot;&gt;my parish&lt;/a&gt; here in town and was chrismated into the Church and I’ve never looked back. Here’s why:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;i-dont-have-to-figure-it-all-out&quot;&gt;1. I don’t have to figure it all out.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Sunday mornings, when Fr. George begins to preach his homily, I listen and take what he teaches as spiritual food and edification. I do the same thing no matter which parish I visit because priests are connected to the Apostolic Tradition. They don’t spend time trying to think up new doctrine or theological opinions, because they participate in the continuation of the preaching and teaching (the kyrgma) of the Apostles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past 2,000 years, there have been countless heresy that have popped up around the world and tried to make in roads into the Church. Those heresies haven’t disappeared, but keep reemerging from various groups and some of them sound appealing. Without keeping constant vigil, it’s easy for one to begin to lean on one’s understanding or get carried off on a tangent that pulls away from the faith once delivered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve heard so many of my friends talk about how they didn’t agree with this pastor or that speaker and I remember the days in college when guest speakers would come and I became so skeptical that I was always waiting for an ax to drop. Some people I’ve talked to have said that’s just the way it is and sometimes their pastor or a speaker says great things and sometimes it’s “Biblically unsound.” Christ warned about false teachers, St. Paul warns against teachers who talk about things contrary to what has been taught and speculating in 1 Timothy, St. John warns about false teachers…the list could go on and on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within Orthodoxy, the Church has guarded the Truth and stands as the &lt;em&gt;”pillar and buttress of the truth”&lt;/em&gt; (1 Timothy 3:15). The Church has held councils as the Apostles did in Acts 15 and was led by the guidance and protection of the Holy Spirit as Christ had promised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;orthodoxy--orthopraxis-go-hand-in-hand&quot;&gt;2. Orthodoxy &amp;amp; Orthopraxis go hand in hand.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Orthodoxy has maintained, over the centuries, that it is the responsibility of the Church to preserve doctrine. Our very name is rooted in that tradition - &lt;em&gt;ortho&lt;/em&gt; meaning right or correct and &lt;em&gt;doxa&lt;/em&gt; meaning belief. &lt;strong&gt;Most&lt;/strong&gt; Christian traditions and sects have a concept of Christian belief, but what is missing is the idea of Christian Practice, or that there is even a concept of right practice. In Orthodoxy, the two are inseparable, but throughout much of the West this is a foreign idea. There is no hesitation or question of understanding when someone says that he or she is an Observant Jew, but there exists very little concept of an Observant Christian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our faith is put into practice in our doctrine and in our lives. The two are not mutually exclusive but built upon one another. As St. James tells us, we are “justified by works and not by faith alone” because “faith by itself, if it does not have works, is dead” (2:24; 17).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what does that look like? Within the Church, we &lt;em&gt;“stand firm and hold to the traditions&lt;/em&gt;” that were delivered by the Apostles, &lt;em&gt;”either by spoken word or by our letter”&lt;/em&gt; (2 Thessalonians 2:15). We are baptized for the remission of sins, receive the gift of the Holy Spirit, when we gather on the Lord’s Day, we participate in the Eucharist, we recieve the gift of confession, we celebrate together, we fast together, we mourn together…we work as one body of Christ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our every day lives, we are called to holiness, which we often miss. My praxis is challenged when I stand before the icon of Christ and confess our sins to Him in the presence of my priest and spiritual father who councils me and confirms God’s forgiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;we-worship-with-our-whole-being&quot;&gt;3. We worship with our whole being.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Orthodox worship engages all of the senses, taking worship out of a theoretical place, and grounding it here, in something tangible. We cross ourselves, offer metenias, prostrate, process - all forms of worship involving movement, engaging our bodies. As we look around, we are surrounded by the icons of Christ and His saints, we hear the chanting and the bells, we smell the incense, we taste the fountain of immortality in the Eucharist - our whole person is engaged in worship, as it should be because, after all, when God created us He said, “It is good.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our senses being engaged in worship speaks to our view of humankind - we are not evil. Our bodies are not evil. We weren’t created to die, the separation of body and soul is a consequence of the fall, not part of God’s design. Our free will separates us, but it was Christ’s incarnation, a good and loving Christ who put on humanity, that redeemed the material world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;orthodoxy-is-connected&quot;&gt;4. Orthodoxy is connected.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I go to an Orthodox Church, I know what to expect. Every Orthodox Church, throughout the entire world will be participating in the same liturgy I am. I am part of something much larger, part of communities of people I’ve never met with languages and cultural customs I know nothing about. A few years ago, I visited a Serbian parish that was near my parents. I &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; have done my research, but I didn’t and when I got there the entire liturgy was in Serbian. Despite the fact that I obviously don’t understand more than a couple of Serbian words, I was actively involed in the liturgy. I knew what the priest was saying, I knew what the chanters were chanting and I was able to participate in this glorious service, commune and fellowship with my brothers and sisters in Christ after service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the connection is deeper - as I look at the icons on the walls, I am connected with those saints. I am praying the same prayers they prayed, I am singing the same hymns they sang, I am receiving the same Eucharist they received. We are connected as the Church militant in a very real way to the Church invisible because,  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.esvbible.org/Hebrews+12/&quot;&gt;“we are surrounded by so great a cloud of witnesses” (Hebrews 12:1)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;we-dont-begin-or-end-liturgy-we-merely-join-in&quot;&gt;5. We don’t begin or end liturgy, we merely join in.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bible shows us insights into Heaven. In Isaiah, Daniel and St. John’s Apocolypse we see liturgical clothing, prayers and responses, censors and incense, lamps and lamp stands, candles, etc. There is an eternal liturgy taking place before the throne of God with angels and saints crying out to God. When we go to church, our services don’t begin and end, but we join into the prayers of the saints. We can again boldly confess that &lt;em&gt;“we are surrounded by so great a cloud of witnesses”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently we celebrated the Feast of All Saints. During Vespers we read, &lt;em&gt;“As is meet let us acclaim with sacred songs and laudations the divine assembly of the Apostles, Martyrs, and godly-minded priests, and the women most chaste, who throughout the whole world have contested in unshaken faith. For, though they were of earth, they were all united together with the Bodiless of Heaven’s heights, and by their august passion they received most blessed dispassion through Christ God’s grace. And now like steadfast stars that shine upon us, they intercede * with great boldness for our souls.”&lt;/em&gt; It is a beautiful feast that reminds us that the Church militant is not removed from the Church invisible, we share the same Great High Priest in Christ Jesus, the same joy in the hope of the resurrection, and the same prayers for the world and all of humanity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;orthodoxy-embraces-mystery&quot;&gt;6. Orthodoxy embraces Mystery.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an Orthodox Christian, I don’t have to try to explain everything. I know that God is bigger than I am and that my ways truly are not His ways. I know that at some point this saying has become a cliche in the West and, as my friend Jeff Huston pointed out, if you would have asked either of us in our pre-Orthodox days if we believed that, we would have said yes without question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we’re Orthodox, it means something…more. In Orthodoxy, we don’t spend our time reading and studying, trying to find a dogmatic reason for things. We don’t have to explain everything, but leave it to mystery. Take the Eucharist for example. We don’t have a doctrine of Transubstantiation or try to explain how the bread and wine are the body and blood of Christ; we know this to be true and it happens by some Divine Mystery.  As a matter of fact, what are called Sacraments in the West are called Mysteries in the East!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was working on my graduate studies, we spent a great deal of time reading about the unknowability of God. There’s an apophatic approach to describing God. Any terms or attributes that we can ascribe to God are limited and fall short, so we describe what God isn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;corporate-and-individual-worship-is-a-part-of-the-christian-life&quot;&gt;7. Corporate and individual worship is a part of the Christian life.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve heard so many people place emphasis on worship and devotion to God being an individual act and, to a degree, I can get on board. I pray to God, I read the Scriptures and writings of the Church Fathers, and try to sit in the stillness seeking God as all Orthodox Christians are called to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we go to church, all of our Orthodox Churches are all laid out the same - we walk into the narthex, enter into the nave and face the altar. The nave is like a ship carrying us all on the journey of life and faith towards Heaven. We participate in the Liturgy together, which, as its very name implies is the work of the people. We are saved both individually and as a community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;confession-is-freeing&quot;&gt;8. Confession is freeing.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a spiritual father, not just a priest, but someone who knows me inside and out, all of my deepest darkest secrets who helps me navigate through the Christian life. After I’ve prayerfully prepared for Confession, I go to our parish and stand with my priest before the icon of Christ at the front of our parish. As I confess, I make my confession to Christ and sometimes I’m granted the freeing tears of repentance. Once I’ve finished, Fr. George confirms Christ’s forgiveness and the remission of sins. But that’s not all, he counsels me with spiritual wisdom that helps me grow in Christ. The Church, through confession, helps us to rise up and become who we are supposed to be in Christ. We are conformed to the image and likeness of Christ. After I confess, I feel free. The sins that I’ve committed, both out in the open and those that I think have been done in secret, once confessed, lose their hold on me. I no longer feel the weight of guilt, but instead know that I can be more than who I am.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only is it freeing, it is Biblical. One of Christ’s final things Christ bestowed to His Disciples was the authority to forgive sins in Heaven and on earth. We believe the Bible to be inspired and have faith in the work of Christ. That authority to confirm the remission of sins is a great gift that far too many people have thrown aside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-liturgical-calendar-is-a-calendar-for-our-lives&quot;&gt;9. The liturgical calendar is a calendar for our lives.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I always loved Christmas - the decorations, the Christmas music we sang in Church, the reading of the Nativity story. Now I love the rest of the events in Christ’s life, along with the events of the Early Church as well lives of the Theotokos and saints and major events in the life of the Church throughout history. The Israelites remembered important days in which God intervened and helped them as Feast Days, days Christ and the Apostles kept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We celebrated Pascha (Easter) a few months ago, and every day we were reminded that we are in the Paschal season. During the Paschal Season, I find myself singing the Paschal troparion - &lt;em&gt;Christ is risen from the dead, trampling down death by death, and upon those in the tombs bestowing life!&lt;/em&gt; - and the Paschal antiphons, I greet other members of the Church by saying &lt;em&gt;“Christ is Risen”&lt;/em&gt;, and look forward to seeing the Paschal candle every week at Church. After 40 days, we celebrated the Ascension, followed by Pentecost in another 10 days. August 6th is Transfiguration, the Church New Year is September 1st, the Nativity of the Theotokos follows on September 8th, then the Feast of the Elevation of the Cross on September 14th…you get the idea. Plus we celebrate our family members’ (and friends’) patron saint days (or, as we call them, name days). Our year revolves around the Church year. We fast, feast and celebrate together. We have customs and traditions in our parish and at our home. It brings our life in Christ and the life of the Church into our every day in a whole new, yet ancient, way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-church-conforms-us-we-dont-conform-it&quot;&gt;10. The Church conforms us, we don’t conform it.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the Civil Rights march in Selma, Archbishop Demetrius marched and stood next to Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. The Civil Rights movement didn’t alter the Church or change the Church, but the Civil Rights movement was rooted in the unchanging truths evident within the Orthodox Church. Orthodoxy doesn’t change every few decades depending on how society changes, but remains a true and steady witness to Christ throughout history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are called to holiness and the standard or measure of holiness is not something that is subjective or something that changes day to day. As things change or public opinion falters, the Church doesn’t change. Instead, we are called to change, as it should be. There is an idea today that we hold God to humanly standards and conform Him to our own image or ideals - instead we are still in a world in which we are ever changed and molded into God’s image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-liturgy-becomes-a-part-of-you&quot;&gt;11. The liturgy becomes a part of you.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never would have believed it at the time, but looking back, I can see that the churches I grew up in had their own liturgy. You go to church, there was upbeat fun music, it would slow down, the pastor would preach for 40 minutes, the lights would go down and slow music would start playing. It happened every week. While at ORU, I learned that there were formulas for this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within Orthodoxy, the liturgy we use is tried and true - most Sundays we pray the Liturgy of St. John Chrysostom, a liturgy that has been used by the Church since the 4th century!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liturgy guides us, it serves as a beacon in a storm-tossed world  that ensures we are oriented in the right direction and keeps our focus aimed for the Kingdom of God, not just some far off place, but helps us find the Kingdom that is within us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-church-knows-what-we-need-when-we-dont&quot;&gt;12. The Church knows what we need when we don’t.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week, a good friend of mine, our parish chanter, fell in asleep in the Lord. It was fairly sudden and caught me by surprise. While he was in the hospital, on life support, and I went to Vespers for All Saints. The readings were so aptly timed - (Isaiah 43:9-14, Wisdom of Solomon 3:1-9 &amp;amp; Wisdom of Solomon 5:15-6:3). It was comforting to hear the encouragement about the saints. After that, I went with my priest when he prayed the prayers for the departing of the soul from the body. It was emotional and I was lost. I didn’t know what to think, much less what to pray. He fell asleep later that evening. Then when I was at home, I was able to turn to the prayers of the Church which gave me comfort. Then, the following morning, we held a prayer service (Trisagian) for him. The Church was there to give us what we needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same is true of things like fasting. A mother gives her child the medicine he or she needs. I think we can all remember a time from childhood when we were sick and our mom gave us something that didn’t taste very good, but, in the end, it made us better.  The same is true for the Church. When I started in a prescribed fast, it was odd. At first, it was a challenge to overcome, I guess you could say I gamified fasting - if I do this, this, and this I win fasting. Then it was something I didn’t do for a long time or I would look for loopholes around fasting. But, when I started fasting, as tough as it was, it began to make sense. I had to put in the effort that the Church prescribed before I could understand the richness that is set there for usx by Christ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same is true of so many aspects of our lives - our services, our readings, our icons, confession, fasting, the lives of the saints - I could go on and on. The Church, as the body of Christ, is the great hospital for us on earth and is here to take care of us, even if we don’t know what we need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know some of these things may not sound earth shattering, but believe me it is. It’s different within Orthodoxy, it’s healing, it helps us to become whole, it continues the work of Christ in restoring humanity through the guidance and power of the Holy Spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/12-things-i-love-about-orthodoxy/&quot;&gt;12 Things I Love About Orthodoxy&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Thom Crowe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com&quot;&gt;Live Orthodoxy&lt;/a&gt; on June 19, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Feast of Pentecost]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/Pentecost-Reflections/" />
  <id>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/Pentecost-Reflections</id>
  <updated>2015-06-01T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2015-06-01T00:00:00-05:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Thom Crowe</name>
    <uri>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com</uri>
    <email>thom@thomcrowe.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;It’s interesting for me to look at the world around me as we approach the Great Feasts and note how so few people I know observe these Feasts of the Christian faith (save Christmas and, for some, Easter). Growing up, I had never really heard of the Feast of Pentecost as a Christian celebration, it was a foreign concept to me after I joined the Church and now it serves as one of my favorite feasts of the year. Of course I had read about Pentecost, growing up Charismatic, Acts 2 was a pretty popular read, but I didn’t really know that it was celebrated throughout the Christian world much as Christmas had been, and the Jewish feasts of the Old Testament. I grew up Charismatic so Pentecost was a defense for speaking in tongues (not an issue I’m going to delve into, suffice to say, my interpretation of this is dramatically different now), but it’s place as an actual feast recognized every year 50 days after Pascha (Easter) was not there, so I thought I’d share a little on the traditional understanding of the Feast of Pentecost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-history-of-pentecost&quot;&gt;The History of Pentecost&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the Old Testament, Pentecost, which means 50th day, was an agricultural feast that occurred 50 days after Pascha (Passover) and is known by the Jewish faithful as the Feast of the First Fruits, or Shavuot. While an agricultural feast (the end of the harvest season), it is also associated with God giving Moses the 10 Commandments on Mount Sinai. For Christians, Pentecost is the beginning of the ministry of the Apostles. In the upper room, the Apostles (and Mary) sat faithfully waiting as Christ had commanded the arrival of the Holy Spirit. This time, when God meets man, instead of bringing stone tablets written with fire, the fire rested upon the heads of the Holy Apostles and they preached Christ to all who were present. Mount Sinai and the tablets given to Moses foreshadowed what was now fulfilled with the gift of the Holy Spirit to the Apostles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-do-we-need-pentecost&quot;&gt;Why Do We Need Pentecost&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We as Christians also see this as a reversal of the Tower of Babel. People decided that they were not content to rule over the earth, but pride led them to want to acquire heaven by force. They built a tower to reach God and, in turn, God confused the tongues of man. On Pentecost, the Holy Spirit unites humanity together again by the gift of tongues. The hymnography of the Church clearly illustrates this: Of old there was confusion of tongues because of the boldness of the tower-builders. But those tongues have not uttered wisdom for the glory of divine knowledge. There God condemned the infidels to punishment, and here with the Spirit Christ illuminated the fishermen. At that time, the confusion of tongues was designed for vengeance, and now the unison of tongues hath been renewed for the salvation of our souls. – the Doxasticon of Pentecost When the High One descended, confusing tongues, He divided the nations. And when He distributed the fiery tongues He called all to one unity. Wherefore, in unison we glorify the most Holy Spirit. – the Kontakion of Pentecost. As &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archbishop_Dmitri_Royster&quot;&gt;Archbishop +DMITRI&lt;/a&gt; (memory eternal) wrote in his &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pravoslavie.ru/english/62291.htm&quot;&gt;article on Pentecost&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“What happened on that fiftieth day after our Lord’s resurrection was the filling of the disciples with the Holy Spirit, their transformation into the Church. Pentecost is the day of the Church’s founding. From this point in time the disciples were empowered to do what our Lord told them: ‘As my Father hath sent me, even so send I you.’” (John 20:21).”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pentecost Icon And at Orthros we sing: The spring of the Spirit hath come to those on earth, dividing noetically into fire-bearing rivers, moistening the Apostles and illuminating them. The fire hath become to them a dewy cloud, lighting, and raining flames upon them, from whom we received grace by the fire and the water. Verily the fire of the Comforter hath come and lighted the world. In the Orthodox Church, we switch all of the liturgical colors (vestments, altar cloths, candles, etc) from the joyous white of Pascha, to a green, clearly connecting to the Jewish celebration of Pentecost, as its fulfillment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pentecost-in-the-life-of-the-church&quot;&gt;Pentecost in the Life of the Church&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pentecost is the third of the “Big Three” feasts if you will: on Christmas, God becomes incarnate, humbles Himself takes on humanity with the intent of redeeming creation; on Pascha, God defeats the ultimate enemy of death for us, defeating death by death and restoring humanity to it’s original state through His glorious resurrection; on Pentecost, the third Person of the Trinity, the Holy Spirit descends and gives us what we as followers of Christ need to become perfect. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stmarysgoc.org/fr-anthony-coniaris/&quot;&gt;Fr. Anthony Coniaris&lt;/a&gt; quotes St. Seraphim of Sarov in his article &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theologic.com/oflweb/inhome/pcost.htm&quot;&gt;How To Celebrate Pentecost&lt;/a&gt; at Home by saying :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Prayer, fasting, vigils and all other Christian acts, however good they may be in themselves, certainly do not constitute the aim of our Christian life; they are but the indispensable means of attaining that aim. For the true aim of the Christian life is the acquisition of the Holy Spirit of God. As for fasts, vigils, prayer and almsgiving, and other good works done in the name of Christ, they are only the means of acquiring the Holy Spirit of God.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Let us, O believers, celebrate with joy the last Feast, which is also the last of the Feast—Pentecost—which is the end and fulfillment of the preordained promise; for then did come down the fire of the Comforter upon the earth in the likeness of tongues, lighting the Disciples and revealing them plainly as initiates of heavenly things. Verily, the light of the Comforter hath come and lighted the world” – Kathismata from Orthros. With that in mind, let us begin again to pray: O heavenly King, the Comforter, Spirit of Truth, Who art in all places, and fillest all things, Treasury of good things, and Giver of life, come, and dwell in us, and cleanse us from every stain; and save our souls, O good One.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;further-readings-on-pentecost&quot;&gt;Further Readings on Pentecost&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.goarch.org/special/listen_learn_share/pentecost&quot;&gt;Learn, Listen &amp;amp; Share Pentecost Series&lt;/a&gt; from the Greek Orthodox Archdiocese&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;Phttp://glory2godforallthings.com/2013/06/21/pentecost-and-creation/&quot;&gt;Pentecost &amp;amp; Creation&lt;/a&gt; a great article by Fr. Stephen Freeman&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.antiochian.org/sites/default/files/pentecost.pdf&quot;&gt;Pentecost - The Birthday of the Church: A Theological Reading into the icon of Pentecost&lt;/a&gt; By Fr. Ayman Kfouf&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/Pentecost-Reflections/&quot;&gt;The Feast of Pentecost&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Thom Crowe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com&quot;&gt;Live Orthodoxy&lt;/a&gt; on June 01, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Is Cremation a Good Option?]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/is-cremation-a-good-option/" />
  <id>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/is-cremation-a-good-option</id>
  <updated>2015-05-14T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2015-05-14T00:00:00-05:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Thom Crowe</name>
    <uri>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com</uri>
    <email>thom@thomcrowe.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Before I begin, I fully acknowledge that something like cremation may not &lt;strong&gt;seem&lt;/strong&gt; to be a big theological issue - Christians today are getting cremated all the time and honored with “Celebrations of Life” instead of funerals (but that’s a topic for a whole different article) without giving it much thought. Unfortunately, it is a pretty big issue rooted in ancient heresy and a denial of basic Judeo-Christian beliefs.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;biblical-history-of-the-disposal-of-a-body&quot;&gt;Biblical history of the disposal of a body&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting in Genesis, God was pretty clear with the fact that the body of someone who has fallen asleep in the Lord be buried in the earth. God told Abram (Abraham) that he would be “be buried in a good old age,” and when he died Isaac and Ishmael buried their father, just as the Lord had promised Abraham, next to Sarah (who Abraham had buried) (15:15, 29:9-10, 23:19).  The custom of burying the dead continues throughout the Old Testament: Rachel (Gen. 35:19-20). Isaac (Gen. 35:29), Jacob (Gen. 50), Joshua (Josh. 24:29-30), Eleazar (Josh 24:33), Samuel (1 Sam. 25:1) and David (1 Kings 2:10) were all buried. As a matter of fact, when Moses died, God buried him (Deut. 34:5-6). God lists among Moab’s transgressions the burning of the king of Edom’s bones to lime (Amos 2:1).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s look at the New Testament: Christ was buried - for a few days at least -, Lazarus, John the Baptist and St. Stephen were all buried. There was definintely a pattern set in the Old Testament that carried over into the New Testament of burying the dead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;burial-in-judaism&quot;&gt;Burial in Judaism&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before the time of Christ and to present day, Jewish custom and law does not allow for cremation.  The Talmud shows us that this was a common undertanding within Jewish culture from around the time of Christ when comments on the Torah, “You must bury him in entirety, not partially. From this verse we extrapolate that the command was not fulfilled if the person was partially buried (Nazir 7:1).” Judasim goes so far as to deny burial in a Jewish cemetery for someone who was voluntarily cremated and the laws of mourning are not observed! Why do they care?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Jewish people, to destroy the body denies the resurrection. One is essentially casting away a body as if to say that it’s purpose is done. This is such a great offence that the Mishna teaches that anyone who denies the resurrection, will not be reunited with his or her own body (tractate Sanhedrin 10:1.).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Jewish law, cremation is forbidden because of the belief that the human body belongs to God and is merely on loan to the person and it will be returned to God.  Coupling this with the belief that humanity was made in the image and likeness of God, desecrating the body, including cremation, is seen as a violation to God Himself&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the Jewish people care so much about the treatment of the body in the hopes of the resurrection, how much greater should we as a people care since we have seen Christ’s resurrection and participated in a foretaste of the general resurrection?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;does-it-really-matter&quot;&gt;Does it really matter?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Christians, it definintely matters. We as Christians believe that when God created matter (the universe, the earth, plants, animals and man), it was good. Humanity was created in the image and likeness of God! Nothing else in all of creation can claim such a high station. Humanity was created body, mind (nous) and soul - this was good. Nowhere does God tell us that to seperate the body from the soul is good, but this was a consequence of the fall. Christ took on humanity, putting on flesh and becoming man, to redeem creation again after the fall, and when He raised from the dead, He was resurrected &lt;em&gt;bodily&lt;/em&gt;. When He was crucified, St. Joseph of Arimathea requested His body to give it a proper burial. Our eschatatology teaches that we will be reunited with our bodies. They are not something to just burn, but instead something to take care of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not to mention, our bodies are not ours to destroy. “For do you not know…”
St. Paul prays, that our “and I pray God your whole spirit and soul and &lt;strong&gt;body&lt;/strong&gt; be kept blameless at the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ” (I Thessalonians 5:23). 9 “Or do you not know that your body is a temple of the Holy Spirit within you, whom you have from God? You are not your own, 20 rfor you were bought with a price. So glorify God in your body” (1 Corithians 6:19-20).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-pagan-and-gnostic-practice&quot;&gt;A pagan and Gnostic practice&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creamation has it’s roots in paganism, not in Judeo-Christian practices. We see cremation in places like India where it is closely aligned to a belief in reincarnation, something the Christian faith opposes. While that may not be enough to turn anyone from cremation, the Gnostic implications should be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gnosticism denies that created matter is good. Our bodies are merely shells that we are to leave behind so we can go to our higher being, as our spirit transcends the physical. It’s in Gnosticism that we see the idea that burning a body is okay because it’s just a body, but it’s not. Cremation undermines Christian ontology.  The teaching of respect for the body and burial was so important to early Christians that many risked their own lives to retrieve the body’s of martyrs. The Romans and other pagans knew this and were known to burn the bodies of martyred Christians in an attempt to destory their faith in the resurrection of hte body by rendering it impossible for resurrection. We know God is more powerful than anything that happens to our bodies and can resurrect us no matter what, but the point here is that it was a grevious insult to our forefathers and mothers of the faith to burn their bodies and now we have Chrisitians readily giving their bodies over to the inceneators and crematorium&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pagans, to destroy faith in the resurrection of the body, often cast the corpses of martyred Christians into the flames, fondly believing thus to render impossible the resurrection of the body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christians would lay the bodies of their loved ones in &lt;em&gt;coemeterium&lt;/em&gt;, which is a Latin term that takes it’s name from the Greek word  &lt;em&gt;κοιμητήριον&lt;/em&gt; which means literally “&lt;em&gt;sleeping place&lt;/em&gt;.”  This term reflects the view that the early Christians had of personhood and how it relates to the body. Not to mention, as illustrated previously, the body was not, and should not be seen as something we can dispose of or destroy, because it doesn’t belog to us, but ultimately belongs to God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our bodies are precious, created and fashioned by God as part of who we are in His image and likeness. We were not made to be seperated from our bodies and will once again be reunited with them for all of eternity. Maybe they are something we should plan to give honor and respect to, even after we’ve fallen asleep in the hope of the resurrection.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/is-cremation-a-good-option/&quot;&gt;Is Cremation a Good Option?&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Thom Crowe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com&quot;&gt;Live Orthodoxy&lt;/a&gt; on May 14, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Switching to Jekyll]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/switching-to-jekyll/" />
  <id>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/switching-to-jekyll</id>
  <updated>2015-03-15T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2015-04-01T00:00:00-05:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Thom Crowe</name>
    <uri>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com</uri>
    <email>thom@thomcrowe.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;h2 id=&quot;switching-blog-platforms&quot;&gt;Switching blog platforms&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I launched my new website, I decided to reevaluate the platform I was using. With my awesome job, I had to learn to be comfortable with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.github.com&quot;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; and taken a course to learn Ruby, so I thought I’d look at a few other options. I’ve used Blogger (which I found limiting) and then moved to WordPress, which I had been using for various projects for about 9 years now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;out-with-the-old&quot;&gt;Out with the old&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t get me wrong, WordPress is a great and has several perfect use case scenarios. With a small learning curve, it’s easy to get people on board with and to get started. There is no shortage of themes and plugins available to do whatever it is you need to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I were to need an option for a client who wanted a website that he/she could update or have a team working on, WordPress would be a great CMS that I would still recommend. Several of the sites that my wife and I use are still WordPress. So why not here? I moved from WordPress for a few reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;WordPress becomes bloated and slow.&lt;/em&gt; There are a ton of plugins for WordPress, which is convenient for several use cases. On the flip side, the plugins can slow down. Even when utilizing cacheing, optimizing images, and upgraded hosting, WordPress still gets bogged down.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Want to move away from MySQL and PHP.&lt;/em&gt; Not really such a big deciding factor for me, but I everything on WordPress is stored first and foremost in a database. Like I said, not a huge deal, but there are other options that don’t require databases or server-side language. Moving from WordPress opens up and simplifies hosting.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Markdown isn’t native.&lt;/em&gt; Again, not make or break, but not convienent. I like markdown - it’s easy to learn and simple and fast to use. I can add it to WordPress.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Over Plugins.&lt;/em&gt; Plugins take time. Sure they offer solutions, but you have to keep up with them. Plus, as we’ve learned from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://thehackernews.com/2015/03/wordpress-seo-by-yoast-plugin.html&quot;&gt;recent SEO by Yoast vulnerability&lt;/a&gt;, plugins &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; expose your site to some vulnerabilities. I’d rather not expose my site to those issues. Not to mention, I don’t want to upgrade those and check compatability every few weeks. WordPress is a growing target for hackers.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;WYSIWYG is not WYSIWYG.&lt;/em&gt; What you see is what you get editors don’t work. They just don’t. I still end up needing to use the HTML editor to make my posts look &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; like I want them to with WordPress. I know I can get markdown in WP, but I really don’t feel like dealing with it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-i-looked-into&quot;&gt;What I looked into&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like I said before, WordPress is great. It’s just not for me right now. So I looked at Jekyll, Middleman &amp;amp; Ghost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;middleman&quot;&gt;Middleman&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve worked with Middleman for work and we were looking at starting a Middleman blog. It’s a great static site generator which can blog, kind of like WordPress, which is a blog platform that can generate sites. To build a blog in Middleman, you have to add a blog gem, but it works. Middleman is great for building a site &lt;em&gt;with&lt;/em&gt; a blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ghost&quot;&gt;Ghost&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ghost is really cool and I like the philosophy behind it. Ghost has one goal:
&amp;gt;Ghost is a platform dedicated to one thing: Publishing. It’s beautifully designed, completely customisable and completely Open Source. Ghost allows you to write and publish your own blog, giving you the tools to make it easy and even fun to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pretty cool, huh? They use the MIT open-source license, giving the user freedom to do just about anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The down side? Ghost is built on Node. I don’t have anything particular against Node, but I’m much more comfortable in Ruby. You have to use a Node.js capable server and if you make small changes on your server and you have to restart Node. I want to keep working on making Ruby magic and I’m not ready to jump into Node.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I jump in to why I chose Jekyll, a quick note about &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.medium.com&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt;. I’m  watching the development of Medium and waiting to see where it goes. I like the community that’s developing around Medium, but I’m not sure I’m ready to commit to it for the long term. Plus, I can’t host my own Medium blog, so I’m out (for now).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;jekyll&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m pretty excited by Jekyll to be honest. It’s fast, simple and writing really couldn’t be any easier. Not to mention, I’m running &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/octopress/octopress&quot;&gt;Octopress 3.0&lt;/a&gt; which brings quite a bit of simplicity to the already easy-to-use Jekyll like easily creating and publishing drafts, unpublishing posts, and creating new posts from the command line. Not to mention, Jekyll 3.0 is just around the corner with the promise of upgrades like Liquid 3, incremental regeneration and integrating basic hooks through Octopress. Like Ghost, they use the MIT open-source license, which I really dig.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really like it so far. It’s nice to not deal with server-side software, which, for me, means it just works. I load the page, and it does what it’s supposed to. Since you write your posts for Jekyll in Markdown, you I can use &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sublimetext.com/3&quot;&gt;Sublime Text 3&lt;/a&gt; for blogging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the fact that Jekyll doesn’t have a database. It simplifies things. Developing and testing locally is simple. When I push something live to my site, it works the way I want it to. Couple that with the free hosting option through &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt; and I’m sold. Time will tell, but that’s been my though process behind the switch.&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/switching-to-jekyll/&quot;&gt;Switching to Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Thom Crowe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com&quot;&gt;Live Orthodoxy&lt;/a&gt; on April 01, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[We're Adopting]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/were-adopting/" />
  <id>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/were-adopting</id>
  <updated>2015-03-13 09:34:25 -0500T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2015-03-13T00:00:00-05:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Thom Crowe</name>
    <uri>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com</uri>
    <email>thom@thomcrowe.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;h2 id=&quot;were-adopting&quot;&gt;We’re adopting!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s right, we’re really excited to grow our family through adoption this year (well, hopefully this year). We applied and have been accepted as an adoptive family at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.crisispregnancyoutreach.org&quot;&gt;Crisis Pregnancy Outreach&lt;/a&gt;. So far we’ve met our awesome mentor, had our fingerprints taken , and scheduled our home study. This is going to be an exciting journey and we’ll be blogging on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thomandchristine.com&quot;&gt;our adoption site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most fun things we’ve done in a while is the photo shoot we had with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.erinwilsonphotography.com/blog/the-crowes-adoption-life-book-session-river-valley-arkansas-photographer/?utm_source=thomcrowe.com&amp;amp;utm_medium=blog&amp;amp;utm_campaign=adoption%20announcment&quot;&gt;Erin Wilson&lt;/a&gt; from Erin Wilson Photography. Erin is a very dear friend of ours who volunterred to come to Tulsa from her home in Clarksville, AR when &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.weatherandnoise.com&quot;&gt;Christine&lt;/a&gt; told her what we were planning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The road ahead is still long: we have our home study next week, we’re working on our lifebook, we have 150 volunteer hours to complete with CPO, all while we continue to pray for the birthmother who we have faith will choose us. We ask for your continued prayers for Christine and I as we embark on this journey.&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/were-adopting/&quot;&gt;We&#39;re Adopting&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Thom Crowe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com&quot;&gt;Live Orthodoxy&lt;/a&gt; on March 13, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[My first post in Jekyll]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/my-first-post-in-jekyll/" />
  <id>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/my-first-post-in-jekyll</id>
  <updated>2015-02-28 08:34:25 -0600T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2015-02-28T00:00:00-06:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Thom Crowe</name>
    <uri>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com</uri>
    <email>thom@thomcrowe.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve been working with WordPress for about a decade now and Blogger before that and wanted to play with something new. So, here I’m jumping in to &lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com/jekyll/jekyll&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/octopress/octopress&quot;&gt;Octopress 3.0&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I’m in California for work right now, updates will have to come later.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/my-first-post-in-jekyll/&quot;&gt;My first post in Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Thom Crowe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com&quot;&gt;Live Orthodoxy&lt;/a&gt; on February 28, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Is your church worship more pagan than Christian?]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/christian-worship-or-pagan-worship/" />
  <id>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/christian-worship-or-pagan-worship</id>
  <updated>2015-01-15T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2015-01-15T00:00:00-06:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Thom Crowe</name>
    <uri>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com</uri>
    <email>thom@thomcrowe.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Last week, Christianity.com posted an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.christianity.com/church/worship-and-hymns/is-your-church-worship-more-pagan-than-christian.html&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; posing a great question, “Is your church worship more pagan than Christian?” A friend of mine shared it on Facebook and there was a discussion about the nature and purpose of worship, but there wepre some key points that I think the article neglected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First off, and I know this may be an unpopular view in modern culture, but worship isn’t about feelings. This idea of what I get out of worship or what worship has to offer me is really new on the Christian spectrum. People today go to this church or that church because they like the worship (contemporary, rock, traditional, etc).  To get more people in the door, it’s not uncommon for churches to put on what appear to me to be major concerts. Some churches go so far as to have different worship services at different times to be all things to all men.  The services are made to fit our needs and appeal to our personal preferences as opposed to being grounded in the true Christian faith. This isn’t anything new, the idea that people wanted to worship in their own way is a longstanding issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Israel was plagued throughout the Old Testament with falling short of their calling – God gave them judges, kings and prophets, yet they felt the need to be altered by the world around them, both theologically and liturgically. They had clear instructions on worship from Moses and yet still became idolatrous and worshiped a golden calf (Exodus 32). Things went south, they repented and returned to the straight and narrow. Fast forward to Jeroboam who lead Israel to sin by false worship when he introduced not just one, but two golden calfs (2 Kings 12). The Israelites wanted to worship how they felt was right and disregarded the instructions they had been given.  The worship God gave them wasn’t good enough, so they found other forms to fit their needs, other forms that made them feel good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that was Israel before Christ, it doesn’t really apply to us, does it? I mean, there aren’t churches constructing golden calfs, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-christians-worship-then--now&quot;&gt;How Christians Worship Then &amp;amp; Now&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s look at Christian worship. First off, Christ tells us he didn’t come to destroy the law, but to fulfill it. The Scriptures clearly in tell us that Apostles remained liturgical, they prayed the liturgical hours (Acts 2:42, 5:42, 10:2-3; 9, 16:25), kept a liturgical calendar (Acts 10:6), referred to Christ as the liturgist in the heavenly sanctuary (Hebrews 8:2). The worship of the Early Church was the fulfillment of that found in Israel with the revelation of Christ, and this continued without question for 1,500 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our worship is modeled after the worship in Heaven. Isaiah, Daniel and John all had vision of heaven that were consistent despite spanning well over a millenium. In every case there are elements of liturgical worship (incense/censors, candlesticks, responsory prayer, etc), the same worship prescribed in the Pentetuch/Torah. The book of Revelation clearly illustrates the use of altars (Rev. 6:9, 8:3, 9:13), censors and incense (5:8, 8:3), candles and candle stands (1:12, 4:5), vestments (1:13, 4:4, 6:11, 7:9-13, 15:6), scrolls – like the Gospel book in Orthodox worship – (5:2), and prostration in worship (4:10-11).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the context in which we worship, as it is in heaven, which only makes sense. The Holy Orthodox Church holds to the Traditions as handed down from the Apostles (2 Thess 2:14), which include the use of the Liturgy. That’s the beauty of Orthodoxy – I’ve attended and worshiped in parishes that didn’t speak any English, but the liturgy was the same. I was actively involved though I didn’t know any Serbian or much Greek.  If a fourth century Christian came into my parish tomorrow, he or she would recognize what is happening and feel right at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The New Testament Church was liturgical and centered in the person of Christ Jesus, as is the Orthodox Church does today. When we pray, we still pray the psalms and we still read the Old Testament Scriptures, but we read and pray with the light of Christ’s incarnation, life and resurrection. Israel worshiped on the Sabbath (Saturday), the Church worships on the Lord’s Day (Sunday). Israel had numerous sacrifices in the temple, the Church participates in the sacrifice of Christ offered once and for all each and every Sunday and feast day when we join together in the Eucharistic worship. Theophany is the Feast of Lights, Pascha is the eternal Passover, we celebrate the coming of the Holy Spirit on Pentecost, the Feast of Booths is fulfilled on Transfiguration. I could go on and with how different elements of our worship fulfill the practices of ancient Israel, but the important thing here is that the Church, in her teachings and worship, is the living the fulfillment of Israel through Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-thoughts-on-christian-worship&quot;&gt;Final Thoughts on Christian Worship&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So where &lt;a href=&quot;http://wwww.christianity.com&quot;&gt;christianity.com&lt;/a&gt; asks, “Is your church worship more pagan than Christian?” I think it’s important to ask “Is your church worship more worldly or heavenly?”&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/christian-worship-or-pagan-worship/&quot;&gt;Is your church worship more pagan than Christian?&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Thom Crowe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com&quot;&gt;Live Orthodoxy&lt;/a&gt; on January 15, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Most Wonderful Time of the Year]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/the-most-wonderful-time-of-the-year/" />
  <id>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/the-most-wonderful-time-of-the-year</id>
  <updated>2014-11-24T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2014-11-24T00:00:00-06:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Thom Crowe</name>
    <uri>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com</uri>
    <email>thom@thomcrowe.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Christmas is an exciting time and it is so easy to loose focus on why we’re celebrating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things are changing, the hot days of summer are gone and people have started pulling out the sweaters and coats, more so this year than most thanks to the polar vortex that brought some lovely snow to us here in Tulsa this weekend. This weather was perfectly timed with the start of the Fast of the Nativity to get me to thinking about Christmastime and how we as Orthodox Christians engage during this time year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growing up, Christmas was my favorite time of the year. The holiday was a really BIG event in our evangelical/charismatic church. We would do a candle light service every year where we would sing hymns. This felt Christmassy to me. Then when I was in high school, I attended a candle light mass at a Catholic church with a friend and that was pretty cool too. The churches were all decorated with greenery, big nativity scenes and we had the carols. I associated all ofthese things and songs with Christmas. When I became Orthodox, I really missed the way I had celebrated Christmas growing up a lot of that and really thought out how to reconcile that celebration with my new-found Orthodox celebration.Thirteen Christmases later, I have a few thoughts on this for others who have joined the Church or are looking into it. While this was originally meant to be a single blog post, like so many other times in my life, I found myself adding more and more and more, so this week I’m going to focus on Advent and Christmas music with more to come next week.this will be continued into next week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;advent--the-nativity-fast&quot;&gt;Advent – the Nativity Fast&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our fast in the East begins on November 15th. I personally need the fast to help me stay focused on exactly what we are preparing to celebrate. The world around us is in a frenzied state of hyped up consumerism and unchecked revelry. Even many Christians in the West forget the purpose of the season leading up to Christmas. As everyone else is spinning out of control, the fast reminds us that we need to slow down and focus on Christ. The Incarnation, God becoming man, is an universe-altering event, that we need to really stop and reflect upon. As Orthodox Christians, we fast to bring us closer to God, not because we have to,for show or to create unfair hardship. Saint Cosmas of Aitolia instructs, “Fast according to your ability, pray according to your ability, give alms according to your ability.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-better-time-than-nativity&quot;&gt;What better time than Nativity?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important part of any fast is participation in the liturgical life of the Church. We have rich hymnography and services throughout Advent. To keep everything in focus, the church gives us hymn lyrics like this: “Make ready, O Bethlehem: let the manger be prepared, let the cave show it’s welcome. The truth has come, the shadow has passed away; born of a Virgin, God has appeared to men, formed as we are and making god-like the garment He has put on. Therefore Adam is renewed with Eve, and they call out: ‘Thy good pleasure has appeared on earth to save our kind.’” It is during this time that we remember Israel awaiting the arrival of the Christ child that we know is coming in a few weeks, so that when we arrive at the great Feast, we can sing as St. Symeon the God-receiver, “Lord, now you are letting your servant depart in peace, according to your word; for my eyes have seen your salvation that you have prepared in the presence of all peoples, a light for revelation to the Gentiles, and for glory to your people Israel.” Why does this matter? St. Maximos the Greek (4th century, not to be confused with St. Maximos the Confessor) wrote, “Unless the Lord comes to us, we are completely helpless.” Without the Incarnation, without the birth of Christ, we would not have the door to salvation that has been opened to us through His glorious Resurrection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;christmas-music&quot;&gt;Christmas Music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love Christmas music. I really do. Like, really really love Christmas music. It was always something that was a big deal to listen to in my home growing up and the songs were always a part of church life as well, one of the few vestiges of a liturgical life left in the religious tradition in which I grew up. Over the years, I’ve listened to Western Christmas hymns and studied them to ensure what I was hearing and singing was aligned with Orthodoxy. For the most part, I was really glad to learn that they were. I’m not talking the Jingle Bells or Rudolph or Christmas Shoes songs, I’m talking the O Come, O Come Emmanuel, Angels We Have Heard on High,  God Rest Ye Merry Gentlemen songs. These are amazing. O Come, O Come Emmanuel recalls the need Israel had for a savior, the need all of humanity had for Christ. O Come All Ye Faithful calls the faithful to celebrate the birth of Christ together. Away in a Manager recalls Christ’s birth (though I’d like the cave to be mentioned somewhere in there). The Little Drummer Boy gives us images of finding the Christ child in the manager. We Three Kings recalls the journey of the Magi, Kings from the East, coming to worship the Heavenly King humbled as a young babe. Others like The First Noel, Good King Wenceslas, I Saw Three Ships, Joy to the World, and O Little Town of Bethlehem are great songs to listen to and sing during the Nativity Fast as they continue to point us to Christ and the real reason for the season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others I learned to be leary of. It Came Upon a Midnight Clear was written by a Unitarian with the intent of removing the Incarnational reality from Christ’s birth and Christmas. Unitarians are quick to point out that “the Christ-child is never mentioned” because it is “ethical song, extolling the worth and splendor of peace among men.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That being said, it’s so important to incorporate the beauty of the Orthodox hymnography into Christmas celebrations. I’d venture to say, it’s not possible for one to keep Christ in Christmas more than the Orthodox Church has. If you want to hear some good Orthodox Christmas music, check out the CD Make Ready, O Bethlehem by Anaphora. I can’t really let you hear it here, so I’ll just share some of the beautiful poetry in our Christmas tradition:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Christ is born! Glorify Him!
Christ descends from the heavens, welcome Him!
Christ is now on earth, O be jubilant!
Sing to the Lord, the whole earth,
And sing praises to Him with joy, O ye people,
For He has been exalted!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What shall we present unto Thee, O Christ,
For Thy coming to earth for us men?
Each of Thy creatures brings Thee a thank-offering:
The angels — singing; the heavens — a star;
The Wise Men — treasures; the shepherds devotion;
The earth — a cave; the desert — a manger;
But we offer Thee the Virgin-Mother. O Eternal God, have mercy upon us.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Today doth Bethlehem receive Him
Who sitteth with the Father for ever”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I behold a strange but very glorious mystery:
Heaven — the cave;
The throne of the Cherubim — the Virgin.
The manger — the receptacle in which Christ our God,
Whom nothing can contain, is lying*&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thy Nativity, O Christ our God,
Has illumined the world like the Light of Wisdom&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;… They who worshipped the stars were through a star,
Taught to worship Thee, the Sun of Righteousness,
And to know Thee, the Day-Spring from on high&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check back next week as we talk about decorations, festivities and other aspects of the celebration of the birth of Christ.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/the-most-wonderful-time-of-the-year/&quot;&gt;The Most Wonderful Time of the Year&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Thom Crowe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com&quot;&gt;Live Orthodoxy&lt;/a&gt; on November 24, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Christian Canon - pt 2]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/the-christian-canon-pt-2/" />
  <id>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/the-christian-canon-pt-2</id>
  <published>2014-05-29T07:58:29-05:00</published>
  <updated>2014-05-29T07:58:29-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Thom Crowe</name>
    <uri>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com</uri>
    <email>thom@thomcrowe.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;h2 id=&quot;the-christian-canon---pt-2&quot;&gt;The Christian Canon - pt 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So taking a slight detour in our journey into the Christian canon I started last week, I thought I’d write my ponderings on the Christian Old Testament.  The conversation came up recently and a friend made reference to the “Catholic books of the OT” and talked about how they added to the Bible.  Unfortunately, in the many Evangelical circles, this is the view. So here is a little on the history of the Christian Old Testament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;christian-canon--the-septuagint&quot;&gt;Christian Canon &amp;amp; The Septuagint&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About 200 years before the time of Christ, the need arose for Jews of the Diaspora (those who found themselves, for various reasons, outside of Jerusalem) to have the Scriptures translated into a language they understood and since Greek was &lt;i&gt;lingua franca&lt;/i&gt; (the language of the people), it only made sense they would be translated into Greek.  This work was called the Septuagint, a name given based on the story that 70 scholars were called together to translate the Scriptures and as the story tells, they all had the same translation. What we do know for a fact is that the Septuagint came from Alexandria and, since Greek was the language used by the people, it quickly gained favor throughout the Greek empire (and later Roman) and was used by the Jews in synagogues.  This translation was in use by the Jews for centuries and, for the Jews of Christ’s time, was a well-used and highly-favored translation of the Scriptures.  Jewish writers like Philo of Alexandria and Josephus drew heavily upon the Septuagint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I know I’m going to digress into random interesting info that I’m not really sure adds to the discussion, but that I find interesting.  So for obvious reasons, the Jews have never called the Old Testament “Old Testament” because that would imply a New Testament or an Older Testament or something, but since they don’t have these, they have what they call the Tanakh.  This word is derived from the divisions made which are the Torah (the first five books of the Bible, or the Books of Moses: Genesis, Exodus, Leviticus, Numbers, and Deuteronomy),  the Nevi’im (the Prophets: Joshua, Judges, I &amp;amp; II Samuel, I &amp;amp; II Kings, Isaiah, Jeremiah, Ezekiel, and a book that consists of what we call the minor prophets known as the book of the Twelve Prophets- Hosea, Joel, Amos, Obadiah, Jonah, Micah, Nahum, Habakkuk, Haggai, Zechariah, and Malachai ), and the Ketuvim (the writings: Psalms, Proverbs, Job, Song of Solomon, Ruth, Lamentations, Ecclesiastes, Ester, Daniel, Ezra/Nehemiah, and I &amp;amp; II Chronicles).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Jewish leaders stopped using the Septuagint sometime during the second century CE, but that means it was a valid text for the Jewish faithful for 300-500 years. One of the reasons argued for the discontinued use of the Septuagint is because it had been used so heavily by the Christians and was used in dialogue and apologetics of the Christians against Judaism. During this time it was adopted by Christians and remained the near universal text for Christians until the Protestant reformation beginning around the 1500’s, 1500 years after the death of Christ, when protestant reformers began to prefer the Hebrew manuscripts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-official-christian-canon&quot;&gt;The Official Christian Canon?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we believe as some Protestant scholars have, that the “official” translation at the time of Christ was the Hebrew, then sadly, much of the New Testament is in error as the writers quoted from the Septuagint. One great example is the St. Matthew’s use of the word &lt;i&gt;virgin&lt;/i&gt; when quoting Isaiah in 1:23 when he discusses the birth of Christ; while the Hebrew manuscripts use the term “young woman” the Septuagint manuscripts say “virgin. For more, check out this &amp;lt;a title=“&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.oncedeliveredfaith.com/septuagint-in-the-new-testament/&quot;&gt;Septuagint in the New Testament&lt;/a&gt;. When Jesus is quoted by the Gospel writers, they do so in Greek, implying that not only did the Apostles consider the Septuagint valid, but Christ did also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Hebrew manuscripts used are called the Masoretic texts since they were the texts of the Masoretes who added marks above and below the text to signify the vowels and accents since Hebrew had no vowels.  This standardization occurred between the 8&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; and 10&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; centuries CE, which means, these texts were interpreted and standardized nearly a millennia after the death of Christ.  With the discovery of the Dead Sea Scrolls, we learned that in several cases of the textual differences between the more modern Hebrew manuscripts and the Septuagint, the ancient Hebrew manuscripts favored the Septuagint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The New Testament writers and the Church Fathers almost unanimously used the Septuagint, yet for some reason, there exists a bias against the Septuagint, part of which comes from the fact that Septuagint contains some books called by some &lt;em&gt;deuterocanonical&lt;/em&gt; (another canon -  I don’t like this term from a Christian perspective since this was part always of the OT canon of the Church) or &lt;a href=&quot;http://orthodoxwiki.org/Apocrypha&quot;&gt;apocrypha&lt;/a&gt; (literally meaning hidden or secret, again, I really do not like this term because these books were never hidden or secret).  The books in question are I &amp;amp; II Esdras, Tobit, Judith, I, II, III, &amp;amp; IV Maccabees, the Prayer of Manasseh, Wisdom of Solomon, the Letter of Jeremiah, Baruch, and Sirach as well as an additional Psalm, additions to Daniel (Song of the Three Holy Youths, Susanna, and Bel &amp;amp; the Dragon), and Esther.  Origen’s &lt;em&gt;Hexapla&lt;/em&gt; (the first known parallel Bible) included the Septuagint.  St. Lucien of Antioch published an addition of the Old Testament called the &lt;em&gt;Loukianos&lt;/em&gt; which was in use in the fourth century in Constantinople and Antioch.  Hesychius included the books in his Old Testament used in Egypt. The Council of Hippo (393) &amp;amp; Carthage (397) confirmed the use of these books as Scripture. Yet, some books of the Septuagint were removed from the canon by Protestant reformers who decided the Jewish canon of the 10th century was more credible than the Christian canon in use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-christian-canon---the-orthodox-old-testament&quot;&gt;The Christian Canon - The Orthodox Old Testament&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Orthodox Church fortunately wasn’t confronted with Reformation movement.  To this day, the Orthodox Church uses the Septuagint as it’s Old Testament source and Canon.  This is the compilation that has been used since the time of Christ (not to mention that Christ Himself quoted!).  We have not added or taken away any books from the Old Testament, but instead keep the Old Testament as it was throughout much of the world at the time of Christ.  Our canon has not been decided upon based on what was accepted by the Jewish community after the death of Christ, but instead what was used by the Apostles and their successors.   Fortunately for us, we have the Orthodox Study Bible, released by Thomas Nelson Publishers, which is an Orthodox translation of the Septuagint, giving us an English translation of the Septuagint to use.   The Septuagint has many great lessons and stories that do provide spiritually edification and have a great deal to offer to Christians today (I myself love the &lt;a href=&quot;[https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Tobit+1&amp;amp;version=RSVCE&quot;&gt;Book of Tobit&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more info, here’s a great intro video&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/p7H6wJ43K_s&quot; width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;allowfullscreen&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/the-christian-canon-pt-2/&quot;&gt;The Christian Canon - pt 2&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Thom Crowe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com&quot;&gt;Live Orthodoxy&lt;/a&gt; on May 29, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Christian Canon - pt 1]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/the-christian-canon-pt-1/" />
  <id>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/the-christian-canon-pt-1</id>
  <published>2014-05-20T07:58:29-05:00</published>
  <updated>2014-05-20T07:58:29-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Thom Crowe</name>
    <uri>http://www.liveorthodoxy.com</uri>
    <email>thom@thomcrowe.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;I thought I’d write briefly on the canon of Scripture, but, as it is with everything I do and say, it ended up being not so brief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lately, I’ve been drawn to reading the Scriptures much more in depth than I have in almost a decade. So I decided to listen to Ancient Faith Radio’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ancientfaith.com/podcasts/searchthescriptures&quot;&gt;Search the Scriptures&lt;/a&gt; and I’ve taken up another round of study over Genesis (which has been an obsession for me, &amp;amp; namely the creation narratives).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Jeannie Constantinou really got me thinking about the canon in her podcast (which I strongly recommend). Allow me to preface by saying that it is in no way my intent to downplay the role of the Bible; you only need to attend one Orthodox service, any service, to see the importance of the Bible in our Tradition is beyond obvious. Also, this is my personal work and I do not claim to speak as an authority on Orthodoxy here, in any blog entry, or anywhere else. With that in mind, here goes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growing up I remember hearing (and saying) things like, “All I need is Jesus and my Bible. &lt;a href=&quot;http://orthodox-apologetics.blogspot.com/2013/07/roberts-articles-on-sola-scriptura.html&quot;&gt;Sola Scriptura&lt;/a&gt; was so engrained in my belief system that anything else seemed ludicrous; I mean, that’s how it was for the early Christians…right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back, I guess I subconsciously thought once each Gospel, Epistle, Acts, and Revelation were written, they were immediately copied and given to every Church who placed a copy in the hands of all of the faithful and they took their Bibles to church, sat in pews, had some praise and worship, then listened to a sermon and they were out. I hadn’t really thought this out too well, but instead just took at face value what I had known.  The liturgical life of the early Church will be yet another topic for yet another day, but, for now, back to the canon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dating of the books of the New Testament is not something there is a strong consensus on, but the earliest estimates are that the books were begun around 40 AD and completed at the end of the 1st century (90-100AD). Even after they were written, it is impossible to think every church received every book and, even the books the various churches had, were not immediately valued as on the same level as scripture as the Old Testament books. There is of course evidence that the writings of the Apostles were soon received as inspired; for example, St. Justin Martyr’s first apology discusses the “memoirs of the Apostles” (the Gospels) being read in the Churches along with the Old Testament as early as the end of the first century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The early church really did not see a need to dogmatize the writings of the Apostles into a canon and, as an aside, the first proposal for a canon came from the heretical teacher Marcion in the mid to late second century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marcion was born in Sinope and made his way to Rome where he began teaching that the Christian God and the God of the Jews (the God of the Old Testament) were, in fact, incompatible and thus not the same, but instead were two separate gods. As a result, Marcion rejected the Old Testament completely , since that was the other God, and sought to make a Gospel that followed his theological perspective. He only accepted the Gospel of Luke as authoritative (even though he edited out everything that related to the Old Testament) and 11 of the letters of St. Paul. From everything I’ve studied, this is the first attempt to form a canon of the New Testament. Despite the obvious heresy and the intent of Marcion (who set up a church hierarchy for his followers alongside the Christian hierarchy as what he believed to be the true Christianity), Marcion began a discussion about the canon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;St. Irenaeus of Lyons, an early Church Father and apologist, argued for the use of Four Gospels. For St. Irenaeus, the four Gospels made up a tetramorph, which literally means symbolic arrangement of four elements, illustrating a canon of the Gospels that existed by the tradition of the Church. For St. Irenaeus, the idea of the four Gospels was logical when he writes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;*The Gospels could not possibly be either more or less in number than they are. Since there are four zones of the world in which we live, and four principal winds, while the Church is spread over all the earth, and the pillar and foundation of the Church is the gospel, and the Spirit of life, it fittingly has four pillars, everywhere breathing out incorruption and revivifying men…For the cherubim have four faces, and their faces are images of the activity of the Son of God. For the first living creature, it says, was like a lion, signifying his active and princely and royal character; the second was like an ox, showing his sacrificial and priestly order; the third had the face of a man, indicating very clearly his coming in human guise; and the fourth was like a flying eagle, making plain the giving of the Spirit who broods over the Church. Now the Gospels, in which Christ is enthroned, are like these.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where the idea of the connection to Matthew and the angel, Mark and the lion, Luke and the ox, and John to the eagle comes from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This entry is long enough, I think, so I’m changing the title of it to The Christian Canon, pt 1 and will continue next week.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com/the-christian-canon-pt-1/&quot;&gt;The Christian Canon - pt 1&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Thom Crowe at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveorthodoxy.com&quot;&gt;Live Orthodoxy&lt;/a&gt; on May 20, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>

</feed>
